<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>TESS</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/</id><updated>2020-06-12T14:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>TESS Weekly Bulletin: June 12th</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-weekly-bulletin-june-12th.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-12T14:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-12T14:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Rebekah Hounsell</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2020-06-12:/docs/tess/tess-weekly-bulletin-june-12th.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;STATUS UPDATE: Reprocessed TESS Data is Coming Soon! - reprocessed data for Sectors 1-19 will be ingested into the MAST archive over the next few months. See the &lt;a href="https://archive.stsci.edu/contents/newsletters/june-2020/reprocessed-tess-data-coming-soon?filterPage=news&amp;amp;filterName=news-filter"&gt;MAST News page&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello TESS followers and welcome to this weeks news bulletin! This week we have three papers from …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;STATUS UPDATE: Reprocessed TESS Data is Coming Soon! - reprocessed data for Sectors 1-19 will be ingested into the MAST archive over the next few months. See the &lt;a href="https://archive.stsci.edu/contents/newsletters/june-2020/reprocessed-tess-data-coming-soon?filterPage=news&amp;amp;filterName=news-filter"&gt;MAST News page&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello TESS followers and welcome to this weeks news bulletin! This week we have three papers from the archive. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.03012"&gt;Photometric detection of internal gravity waves in upper main-sequence stars. II. Combined TESS photometry and high-resolution spectroscopy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Bowman et al., 2020):&lt;/em&gt;
This paper combines high precision TESS light curves with high resolution ground based spectroscopy for 70 O and B stars to test the relationship between photometric signatures and internal gravity waves parameters. 
Internal gravity waves are thought to occur in massive stars via turbulent core convection and from turbulent pressure fluctuations in surface layers.&lt;br /&gt;
The authors determine that there is a relationship between the location of a star on the spectroscopic Hertzsprung-Russell diagram and the amplitudes and frequencies of its random light curve variability. The macroturbulent velocity broadening in the spectral lines of these stars are also correlated to the properties of the stochastic variability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.04126"&gt;Mode identification in three pulsating hot subdwarfs observed with TESS satellite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Sahoo et al 2020):&lt;/em&gt;
Within this paper three pulsating subdwarf B (sdB) stars are examined using TESS data, TIC 067584818, TIC 169285097, and TIC 457168745. In each star a few tens of frequencies/ oscillations are detected. No multiplets were detected in this work. Using high precision trigonometric parallaxes from Gaia and spectral energy distributions the atmospheric parameters were converted into stellar ones. The Radii, masses and luminosities for these three stars are typical for extreme horizontal branch stars (mass ~0.47Msun).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.02106"&gt;The GALAH survey: Lithium-rich giant stars require multiple formation channels&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Martell 2020):&lt;/em&gt;
In this paper data from GALA, K2-HERMES and TESS-HERMES are used to instigate the properties of 1306 red giant stars with high photospheric abundances of Lithium (Li). The paper aims to understand proposed mechanisms for lithium enrichment in giant stars. The authors confirm that Li giant stars are rare and make up only 1.1% of the sample examined. Further analysis revealed that red clump stars are three times more likely to be Li-rich as red giant branch stars, and that the occurrence rate of Li richness with metallicity is different between the two populations. The likelihood of a rapidly rotating giant being Li rich is higher than a non rapid rotator, independent of its evolutionary state. Stars on the red clump which rapidly rotate have extreme levels of Li enrichment, where as no stars on the secondary red clump have Li abundances above the primordial level. The authors work indicates that there is a mass dependence in the Li enrichment mechanism. The complex distribution of Li indicated in this paper suggests that there are multiple independent mechanisms for Li production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Sahoo" src="images/sahoo.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fig 1:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Taken from Sahoo et al., (2020). Upper panel presents the TESS light curves, nottom panel the amplitude spectra. Green horizonal line is the 4.5 sigma threshold.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Reprocessed TESS data coming soon</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/reprocessed-tess-data-coming-soon.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-12T12:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-12T12:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Knicole Colon</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2020-06-12:/docs/tess/reprocessed-tess-data-coming-soon.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS mission will be delivering reprocessed data for Sectors 1-19. These data will be ingested into the MAST archive over the next few months. A full list of the changes to the data will be described in the Data Release Note 30 that will accompany the first set of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS mission will be delivering reprocessed data for Sectors 1-19. These data will be ingested into the MAST archive over the next few months. A full list of the changes to the data will be described in the Data Release Note 30 that will accompany the first set of reprocessed data. Users can refer to the data release number in the headers of the data files in order to distinguish between the new and original data files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the reprocessed data are ingested, MAST will only be making accessible the newer version of the light curve, target pixel and FFI files for each sector. Only the reprocessed data will be available through the MAST services, including the Portal, &lt;a href="https://mast.stsci.edu/tesscut/"&gt;TESScut&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://exo.mast.stsci.edu/"&gt;exo.MAST&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://registry.opendata.aws/tess/"&gt;Amazon Web Services&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://archive.stsci.edu/tess/bulk_downloads.html"&gt;bulk downloads&lt;/a&gt;. The Data Validation files associated with the TESS planet search TCEs will continue to be available for both the original data and the reprocessed data through the MAST portal and bulk downloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data availability tables on the &lt;a href="https://outerspace.stsci.edu/display/TESS/TESS+Holdings+Available+by+MAST+Service"&gt;TESS Holdings Available by MAST Service&lt;/a&gt; page will be updated to indicate which sectors of reprocessed data are available through the different MAST Services as it is being ingested. Prior to a sector being ingested, the original data files will be taken down. As a result the MAST expects data for that sector to be unavailable for ~1 day while the new data is being ingested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first sectors to be reprocessed are those in the northern hemisphere, Sectors 14-19, followed by the southern hemisphere Sectors 1-13. The ingest of these data files will begin in mid-June at a cadence of one reprocessed sector becoming live each week except when new TESS data is available. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Fifth TESS Weekly Bulletin</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/fifth-tess-weekly-bulletin.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-03T22:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-03T22:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Rebekah Hounsell</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2020-06-03:/docs/tess/fifth-tess-weekly-bulletin.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;STATUS UPDATE: Cycle 3 selections have now been made!&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello TESS followers, and welcome to our fifth news bulletin! This week we are happy to announce the selection of our Cycle 3 extended mission targets, and highlight several papers now listed on arXiv.org.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within Cycle 3 selected programs loosely …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;STATUS UPDATE: Cycle 3 selections have now been made!&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello TESS followers, and welcome to our fifth news bulletin! This week we are happy to announce the selection of our Cycle 3 extended mission targets, and highlight several papers now listed on arXiv.org.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within Cycle 3 selected programs loosely fell into the following categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exoplanets: 16&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stellar astrophysics + asteroseismology: 3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extragalactic science: 8&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Binary stars: 16&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cool star activity: 4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solar system science: 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week's paper highlights are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.01721"&gt;A search for young exoplanets in Sectors 1-5 of the TESS Full-Frame-Images&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Battley et al., 2020)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;
This paper aims to study young exoplanets which represent an important aspect of exoplanet research as they allow us to learn about formation and early evolution. Finding a young exoplanet is however difficult because of fast rotation and the activity of their host stars. Many pipelines struggle to deal with the complexities of such systems. The paper presents the LOWESS-based pipeline which is designed to de-trend young stellar light-curves from TESS’s 30min-cadence Full Frame Images (FFIs). The pipeline is applied to sectors 1-5 of the TESS data and although no new candidates are found the authors did recover the signal of the young exoplanet DS Tuc Ab, a number of young eclipsing binaries and a wide array of interesting rotation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.00946"&gt;TESS photometry of extreme helium stars PV Tel and V821 Cen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Jeffery et al., 2020)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;
TESS observations of two bright PV Tel variables are presented within this paper. PV Tel variables are EHe stars, known to show variability on timescales of 0.1 - 25 days. PV Tel stars examined in this paper are V821 Cen and PV Tel itself. The variability found in this paper for PV Tel is consistent with previous observations, whereas V821 Cen is observed to vary for the first time. The light-curves for the two objects do not show underlying regularity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.14201"&gt;The ASAS-SN Catalog of Variable Stars VIII: "Dipper" Stars in the Lupus Star-Forming Region&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Bredall et al 2020)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;
T Tauri-like "dipper" stars are the focus of this paper. These young stellar objects show variations caused by the  partial occultation of the star by circumstellar dust. Observations of these objects inform us of the planet-forming zones around the stars. The authors have examined 11 dipper stars in the Lupus star forming region in data from the All-Sky Automated Survey for Supernovae. The objects are characterized in this paper using data from the Las Cumbres Global Observatory Telescope and TESS (+ additional archival data). The authors determine that all stars examined are above or red-ward of the zero-age main sequence and have infrared excesses which suggest the presence of full circumstellar disks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="v821cen" src="images/v821cen.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fig. 1:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Taken from Jeffery et al., (2020): TESS light curves for PV Tel and V821 Cen which have been resampled into  30 min bins.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Cycle 3 selected programs announced</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/cycle-3-selected-programs-announced.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-01T11:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-01T11:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2020-06-01:/docs/tess/cycle-3-selected-programs-announced.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On July 4, 2020 TESS will begin its extended mission. This also marks the beginning of Cycle 3 of the TESS GI program. There are a number of changes in how TESS operates that start with Cycle 3, including a new 20-s cadence mode, all FFI data being taken at …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On July 4, 2020 TESS will begin its extended mission. This also marks the beginning of Cycle 3 of the TESS GI program. There are a number of changes in how TESS operates that start with Cycle 3, including a new 20-s cadence mode, all FFI data being taken at 10-min cadence and a 10-fold increase in the number of GI program targets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are excited to announce the &lt;a href="approved-programs.html"&gt;selected programs&lt;/a&gt; from the Cycle 3 review of proposals. This was a particularly competitive process this year, with over 150 proposal received. The science investigations selected cover a broad range of topics, from studies of comets in our own Solar System to searching for the counterparts of gamma-ray bursts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the selected programs get the top priority slots for 20-s and 2-min cadence target observations, we will be able to select many more targets for observation than we can support through funding. Therefore, a large number of the programs submitted will have targets selected for observation. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Fourth TESS Weekly Bulletin</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/fourth-tess-weekly-bulletin.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-27T22:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-27T22:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Rebekah Hounsell</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2020-05-27:/docs/tess/fourth-tess-weekly-bulletin.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Welcome TESS followers to our fourth  news bulletin! This week has been another big one with many papers featuring TESS data published on the archive, as such we have chosen to focus on just a few, but well done to everyone again this week!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.10394"&gt;The Pre-He White Dwarfs in Eclipsing …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Welcome TESS followers to our fourth  news bulletin! This week has been another big one with many papers featuring TESS data published on the archive, as such we have chosen to focus on just a few, but well done to everyone again this week!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.10394"&gt;The Pre-He White Dwarfs in Eclipsing Binaries. I. WASP 0131+28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Lee et al., 2020)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;
TESS archival data in combination with that from WASP were used to construct detailed light curves and spectra for the post-mass transfer binary star WASP 0131+28, an EL CVn eclipsing binary in a thin disk. These data were used to study the properties of the extremely low mass white dwarfs. Spectra were used to derive an effective temperature of T&lt;sub&gt;eff&lt;/sub&gt; = 10,000K, and radial velocities  of &amp;#120011;&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;sin&amp;#119998; = 55 km. The TESS data were used to obtain accurate fundamental parameters. The mass of the secondary was derived as 0.2 M&amp;#8857;, with a radius of 0.528 R&amp;#8857;, T&lt;sub&gt;eff,2&lt;/sub&gt; of 11,186 K, and L&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; of 3.9 L&amp;#8857;. The parameters derived agree well with the evolutionary sequence for a He-core white dwarf of mass 0.203 M&amp;#8857;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.10281"&gt;10 Years of Stellar Activity for GJ 1243&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Davenport et al., 2020)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;
GJ 1243 is a flaring M4 dwarf and has been used for studying stellar flare and star spot activity. Data from the Kepler mission was used in the past to study this object, but now new TESS data has been utilized to obtain precise stellar activity characterization for this object over more than a decade. Within the TESS 2-minute cadenced data 133 flare events were detected. These events were used to determine that the flare activity is unchanged between the Kepler and TESS epochs.  Star spots were also found to be consistent between the two data sets, indicating that this object does not show signs of solar-like activity cycles over 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.10253"&gt;PTFO 8-8695: Two Stars, Two Signals, No Planet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Bouma et al 2002)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;
This paper examines the signal from PTFO 8-8695 a star in the 7-10 million year old Orion-OB1 cluster. The star presents dips in its light curve similar to planetary transits, but previous evidence against a planet has been put forth. Using TESS and Gaia data the authors re-examine this object. TESS data indicate two photometric periods, one at 11.98 hrs thought to be caused by stellar rotation, the other at 10.76 hrs and possessing a signal similar to that for planetary transits. It is difficult to interpret the dips as planetary based since their  phase is nearly 180&amp;#176; away from the phase of the originally reported dips. The paper goes on to  considers PTFO 8-8695 as a pair of young and rapidly rotating M dwarfs, one of which is causing the  “transient-dipper” behavior that has been seen in a newly emerging transient class of stars. The physical origin of the dips is still unknown, but likely due to  circumstellar material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="wasp" src="images/wasp.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fig. 1:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Taken from Lee et al., (2020): Light curves of WASP 0131+28 with fitted models. The black circles are from TESS, the gray from LOAO. The solid lines are synthetic curves from a simultaneous analysis of all curves. The lower plot shows the differences between the data and the models.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="gj1243" src="images/gj1243.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fig. 2:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Taken from Davenport et al., (2020): Cumulative flare frequency distribution for the 6107 flares observed with Kepler (black line - Davenport et al., 2014), and 133 flares from TESS (blue line). Flares are sorted large to small with regards to the energy of events per day.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Third TESS Weekly Bulletin</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/third-tess-weekly-bulletin.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-21T14:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-21T14:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Rebekah Hounsell</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2020-05-21:/docs/tess/third-tess-weekly-bulletin.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello TESS followers and welcome to our third news bulletin! This week it's a big one as we have lots of TESS papers featured on arXiv.org, you have all been very busy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.09187"&gt;The Pulsation Properties of &amp;#955; Bootis Stars I. The Southern TESS Sample&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Murphy et al., 2020)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;
This …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello TESS followers and welcome to our third news bulletin! This week it's a big one as we have lots of TESS papers featured on arXiv.org, you have all been very busy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.09187"&gt;The Pulsation Properties of &amp;#955; Bootis Stars I. The Southern TESS Sample&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Murphy et al., 2020)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;
This paper uses TESS data/light-curves to analyzes a sample of 70 Southern Hemisphere &amp;#955; Bootis Stars. From these data the authors identify binaries and determine which of the targets pulsate as &amp;#948; Scuti stars.  Four objects were discovered to be binaries, two heartbeat and two eclipsing. In total 81% of the sample examined pulsate as 948 Scuti stars, this is twice that of normal starts over the same parameter space. Of the &amp;#955; Bootis Stars examined 40 have TESS 2min cadence data, this was used to determining  the temperatures, luminosities and &amp;#948; Scutii variability of the targets . &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.07756"&gt;Optimized cutting off transit algorithm to study stellar rotation from PLATO mission light curves&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Almeida et al., 2020)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; 
With in this paper the authors use their DiffeRencial flUx Method of cuTting Off biNariES (DRUM TONES) algorithm to measure the stellar rotation in eclipsing binaries or planetary systems. There are many complications to such a task including disentangling the signal from the stellar rotation from the transit signal of a stellar or sub-stellar companion. The authors apply their method to TESS data as well as that from other missions. Their method shows a good agreement in the determination of stellar rotation periods for the few observed targets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.07710"&gt;Flare Statistics for Young Stars from a Convolutional Neural Network Analysis of TESS Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Feinstein et al., 2020)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;
A convolutional neural network (CNN) called &lt;em&gt;Stella&lt;/em&gt; has been trained to find flares in TESS short cadenced data. The CNN was applied to 3200 young stars to evaluate flare rates as a function of age and spectral type. The rotation periods for 1500 targets were also measured and it was found that flares of all amplitudes are present across all spot phases, and as such that the spot coverage is high across the entire surface. The study also examines the flare rates and amplitudes across all stellar ages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.07559"&gt;Discovery of 946 Cep pulsations in the eclipsing binary V453 Cygni&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;em&gt;(Southworth et al., 2020)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;
The paper examines V453 Cyg, an eclipsing binary which contains two stars of mass 14 and 11 M&amp;#8857;, in an eccentric short period orbit. &amp;#946; Cep type pulsations were discovered within this system, with 7 significant pulses between 2.37 and 10.51 days&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; in the primary. Using TESS data and spectroscopic results the physical properties of the stars were derived to a high precision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.07203"&gt;TESS Data for Asteroseismology: Timing verification&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Essen et al., 2020)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;
This paper addresses the study of astroseismology with TESS and the need for strong timing requirements. The paper studies the potential consistent drift of TESS in its time keeping and the need for calibration or offsets. A simultaneous study of ground- and space-based primary eclipses of several binary streams in the Southern ecliptic Hemisphere was conducted to verify the reliability of the TESS time stamps. The TESS Barycentric time is 5.8 sec too fast, but consistent with zero at the 2.3 sigma level. The authors also test the existence of a drift with a monotonic growth/decay affecting the observations of all stars.  A drift corresponding to sigma_drift = 0.009 sec/day was determined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.07086"&gt;A possible transit of a disintegrating exoplanet in the nearby multiplanet system DMPP-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;em&gt;(Jones et al., 2020)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;
TESS photometry of DMPP-1 is analyzed within this paper. This star is  an F8V type and host to hot super Earths and warm Neptunes. A transiting period of 3.29 days is determined with a depth of 87 ppm, shallower than all pervious TESS discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.06841"&gt;Periodicity search for Pulsar Binaries with TESS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Pal et al.,m 2020)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;
The TESS data set is used to periodically search for pulsar binary candidates via observation of the flux variation thought to come mainly from the stellar companion. From the TESS data the authors look for flux modulation in five pulsar binaries with reported orbital periods, these include  PSR J1023+0038, 3FGL J0523.3-2528, 3FGL J0212.1+5320, 3FGL J0744.1-2523 and PSR J1417-4402. The paper demonstrates how useful TESS data is in identifying the periodicities of redback-like systems. ~&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="v453cyg" src="images/v453cyg.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fig. 1:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Taken from Southworth et al., (2020): TESS light curve of V453 Cyg. The PDC data is given in grey and the SAP in the remaining six colors. The colors indicate the division of the data into the six sets for the polynomial normalization functions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="dmpp1" src="images/dmpp1.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fig. 2:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Taken from Jones et al., (2020): a) TESS Sector 6 SAP flux of DMPP-1, b) the PDC light curve, c) the PDC flux light curve after sigma clipping (blue) and the mean Gaussian Process function (red), d) the cleaned, de-trended and normalized PDC flux used for transit searches.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Second TESS Weekly Bulletin</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/second-tess-weekly-bulletin.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-13T14:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-13T14:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Rebekah Hounsell</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2020-05-13:/docs/tess/second-tess-weekly-bulletin.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;STATUS UPDATE: We are now observing  in sector 25!&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome TESS followers to second news bulletin! This week we have an exciting announcement about Stellar Pulsations, plus an additional three papers published to arXiv.org.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-020-2226-8"&gt;Very regular high-frequency pulsation modes in young intermediate-mass stars&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Bedding et al., 2020)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;
Some stars …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;STATUS UPDATE: We are now observing  in sector 25!&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome TESS followers to second news bulletin! This week we have an exciting announcement about Stellar Pulsations, plus an additional three papers published to arXiv.org.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-020-2226-8"&gt;Very regular high-frequency pulsation modes in young intermediate-mass stars&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Bedding et al., 2020)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;
Some stars can experience pulsations which can be used to probe their internal structure. Such a class of stars are &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Delta_Scuti_variable"&gt;Delta Scuti&lt;/a&gt; stars, which are of intermediate mass and pulsate in interesting and complex ways. Understanding the nature of these pulsations can be extremely difficult, but using the large FoV, and high cadence coverage provided by TESS scientists were able to detect a subset of Delta Scuti stars with regular pulsations. Once these patterns were established the scientists continued their investigation using data from Kepler, and conducted follow up observations using ground-based facilities such as &lt;a href="http://www.keckobservatory.org"&gt;Keck&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href="https://lco.global"&gt;Las Cumbres Observatory&lt;/a&gt;. The detection of clear patterns in these  objects  is significant as now these pulsations can be compared to models and our understanding of these objects improved. For more information  about this  significant discovery please visit the &lt;a href="https://exoplanets.nasa.gov/news/1645/nasas-tess-enables-breakthrough-study-of-perplexing-stellar-pulsations/"&gt;NASA feature webpage&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.05153"&gt;An Unusual Transmission Spectrum for the Sub-Saturn KELT-11b Suggestive of a Sub-Solar Water Abundance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Colon et al., 2020)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;
This paper  presents a detailed glimpse into  the atmospheric properties  of KELT-11b, an inflated  sub-Saturn-mass  planet. Data used in the presented  analysis were from several space-based telescopes including  TESS, &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/hubble/main/index.html"&gt;HST&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/spitzer/main/index.html"&gt;Spitzer&lt;/a&gt;. Major findings  of the paper include a low-amplitude water feature and extremely low  metallicity, both  unusual  features for this planet which challenge atmosphere and formation models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.04491"&gt;Optical Variability of the Dwarf AGN NGC 4395 from the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Burke et al.,  2020)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;
TESS  is  used to create  light-curves of the dwarf AGN in the nearby galaxy NGC 4395. This galaxy hosts a ~10&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; M&amp;#8857; supermassive black hole. Variability is detected on timescales from weeks to hours before reaching the  background noise level. The TESS light-curve can be well fit by a simple dampened random walk model with a dampening time-scale of 2.3 days. The periodogram can be fit with a high frequency slope of -1.88, and a break frequency consistent with the dampening time-scale. The paper uses NGC 4395 to illustrate the fact that TESS data can be used for extragalactic science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.02423"&gt;Photometry and Performance of SPECULOOS-South&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Murray et al., 2020)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; 
TESS observations are used in comparison to simultaneous observations from the ground-based &lt;a href="https://www.eso.org/public/teles-instr/paranal-observatory/speculoos/"&gt;SPECULOOS-South telescopes&lt;/a&gt; to  test the level of precision obtained via the author's automatic pipeline. SPECULOOS is surveying for transiting  terrestrial planets around the nearest and brightest ultra-cool dwarf stars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="KELT-11b" src="images/KELT-11b.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fig. 1:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Taken from Colon et al., (2020): TESS light curve of KELT-11b. The left panel is the complete TESS  light curve from Sector 9, indicated by the gray dots, the  black line is the median  joint transit  light-curve and Gaussian Process (GP)  model. The right panel is the phase fold light curves and residual after correcting the data against the  GP model.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="DeltSct" src="images/DeltSct.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fig. 2:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Visual interpretation of the rapid pulsation Delta Scuti star  HD 31901. This star is in the southern constellation Lepus. Credits: NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center and Simon Murphy, University of Sydney. A video associated with this figure  can be found &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/nBxn6QGWJNM"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>First TESS Weekly Bulletin</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/first-tess-weekly-bulletin.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-06T14:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-06T14:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Rebekah Hounsell</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2020-05-06:/docs/tess/first-tess-weekly-bulletin.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;STATUS UPDATE: Sector 23 data went live at MAST this week and we are currently observing in Sector 24 until May 12.&lt;/code&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome TESS followers! We here in the TESS GI office plan to issue weekly news bulletins to keep you informed of all things TESS related and to also …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;STATUS UPDATE: Sector 23 data went live at MAST this week and we are currently observing in Sector 24 until May 12.&lt;/code&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome TESS followers! We here in the TESS GI office plan to issue weekly news bulletins to keep you informed of all things TESS related and to also highlight your work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below we highlight four papers that were posted to arXiv.org in the last week:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.01684"&gt;Original Research By Young Twinkle Students (ORBYTS): Ephemeris Refinement of Transiting Exoplanets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Edwards et al., 2020)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;
Eight planets are studied in detail and their ephemeris and orbital data are refined. Data used are that from TESS and fully robotic ground-based telescope network. For seven of the planets the authors find that the observed transit time was outside of the predicted uncertainties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.00272"&gt;TESS Asteroseismic Analysis of the Known Exoplanet Host Star HD 222076&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Jiang et al., 2020)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;
Using TESS data the paper presents an asteroseismic analysis of the red giant star HD 222076 (discovered by &lt;a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-3881/153/2/51/pdf"&gt;Wittenmyer et al 2017&lt;/a&gt;) which has a long period giant planet that was discovered via radial velocity measurements. Asteroseismic modeling has determined the mass of the star as 1.12 M&amp;#8857;, with a radius of 4.34 R&amp;#8857;, and an age of 7.4 Gyr. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.00013"&gt;TESS Hunt for Young and Maturing Exoplanets (THYME) II: A 17 Myr Old Transiting Hot Jupiter in the Sco-Cen Association&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Rizzuto et al., 2020)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;
A 17Myr old transiting hot Jupiter was discovered around HIP 67522, a 10-20 Myr old Sco-CenO OB  star. The orbital period of the planet was identified as 6.96 days with a radius of 10.02 R&amp;#8853;. An additional planet candidate was also identified with an orbital period of ~23 days and a radius of ~8 R&amp;#8853;. The hot Jupiter HIP 67522b is the youngest confirmed transiting hot Jupiter-sized planet discovered to date.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2005.00047"&gt;TESS Hunt for Young and Maturing Exoplanets (THYME) III: a two-planet system in the 400 Myr Ursa Major Group&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Mann et al., 2020)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;
This paper presents the discovery of two planets orbiting a young Sun-like star (M = 0.99&amp;#8857;) HD 63433. HD 63433 was determined to be part of the 414 Myr old Ursa Major moving  group.  The planets have  radii of 2.15R&amp;#8853;, and 2.67R&amp;#8853; respectively, with orbital periods of 7.11 and 20.55 days. The system is important as it will aid our understanding of planetary system evolution in the first billion years after formation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="HIP67522" src="images/HIP67522.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fig. 1:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Taken from Rizzuto et al., (2020): Light curve of HIP 67522 from TESS sector 11. These data have been corrected for systematics using the co-trending bias vector method described in &lt;a href="http://doi.org/10.1086/667697"&gt;Smith et al (2012)&lt;/a&gt; - blue points. The Gaussian Process model from the simultaneous transit and variability of the fit described in Section 5.1  of the paper - black line.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="HD6343" src="images/HD63433v2.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fig. 2:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Taken from  Mann et al., (2020), illustrating the TESS light-curve of HD 63433. The top panel shows the presearch data conditioning simple aperture photometry curve in blue after fitting out the outliers, the Gaussian process model is given in red. The locations of the transits are shown with arrows along the x-axis. The orange represent planet b and the teal planet c.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Replacement of Sectors 20 and 21 data</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/replacement-of-sectors-20-and-21-data.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-04-22T16:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-04-22T16:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Rebekah Hounsell</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2020-04-22:/docs/tess/replacement-of-sectors-20-and-21-data.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sectors 20 and 21 will be replaced with newly exported data files starting April 2020. During the ingest the data files will be a disparate set of both the original and new files. Upon completion of the ingest the check boxes in the &lt;a href="https://outerspace.stsci.edu/display/TESS/TESS+Holdings+Available+by+MAST+Service"&gt;data holdings table&lt;/a&gt; on the MAST website …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sectors 20 and 21 will be replaced with newly exported data files starting April 2020. During the ingest the data files will be a disparate set of both the original and new files. Upon completion of the ingest the check boxes in the &lt;a href="https://outerspace.stsci.edu/display/TESS/TESS+Holdings+Available+by+MAST+Service"&gt;data holdings table&lt;/a&gt; on the MAST website will be replaced with 'v2'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reasons for this re-delivery include changes in how the data quality flags for stray and scattered light are set. It also includes a correction to the time and to the full-frame image (FFI) collateral pixels. For more information, see the 'Memo' listed next to the &lt;a href="http://archive.stsci.edu/tess/tess_drn.html"&gt;data release notes&lt;/a&gt; for DRN27 and DRN29 on the MAST website. These memos's include information on how one can tell the difference between new and old data files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:70%;" src="images/sector-plots/sector-plots.020.jpeg"&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:70%;" src="images/sector-plots/sector-plots.021.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>April 18th marks the two year anniversary of TESS in space</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/april-18th-marks-the-two-year-anniversary-of-tess-in-space.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-04-16T14:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-04-16T14:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Rebekah Hounsell, Knicole Colon</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2020-04-16:/docs/tess/april-18th-marks-the-two-year-anniversary-of-tess-in-space.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Time flies -- it has already been two years since TESS launched into space! Since launching on April 18, 2018, TESS has mapped out a significant fraction of the night sky, confirmed the existence of 45 exoplanets, found more than 1700 planet candidates, and been used to examine the variability of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Time flies -- it has already been two years since TESS launched into space! Since launching on April 18, 2018, TESS has mapped out a significant fraction of the night sky, confirmed the existence of 45 exoplanets, found more than 1700 planet candidates, and been used to examine the variability of countless sources such as active galactic nuclei and supernovae. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before science operations even began in July 2018, &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/feature/goddard/2018/nasa-s-planet-hunting-tess-catches-a-comet-before-starting-science"&gt;TESS managed to capture a set of images showing the motion of the comet C/2018N1&lt;/a&gt;, illustrating TESS's unique ability to collect a set of stable periodic images covering a wide region of the sky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the first few months of operation, TESS demonstrated its planet hunting abilities by detecting its &lt;a href="https://exoplanets.nasa.gov/news/1542/nasas-tess-rounds-up-its-first-planets-snares-far-flung-supernovae/"&gt;first three exoplanets&lt;/a&gt;: a planet named Pi Mensae c, which is twice the size of the Earth and orbits its Sun like star every six days; LHS 3844 b, a rocky planet located in the constellation Indus, at a distance of only 49 light years; a dense non-rocky planet named HD 21749 b, which is three times the size of the Earth and 23 times more massive, making the planet more dense than Neptune.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/feature/goddard/2020/nasa-planet-hunter-finds-its-1st-earth-size-habitable-zone-world/"&gt;TESS discovered its first Earth-size planet in the habitable zone&lt;/a&gt;, which was announced in early 2020. The planet named TOI 700 d orbits a cool M dwarf star approximately 40% the mass and size of the Sun and is just over 100 light years away in the southern constellation of Draco. To date TOI 700 d is one of only a few planets discovered within a system’s habitable zone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/feature/goddard/2020/nasa-s-tess-mission-uncovers-its-1st-world-with-two-stars"&gt;TESS also detected its first circumbinary planetary system in 2019&lt;/a&gt;. The planet, TOI 1338 b, is a world that orbits two stars in the constellation of Pictor, at a distance of 1300 light years. The two stars orbit each other every 15 days - one is 10% more massive than the Sun whilst the other is cooler and dimmer at 1/3 the size of the Sun. TOI 1338 b is believed to be the only planet in the system and is almost 7 times larger than the Earth. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from hunting for planets, TESS, with its almost all-sky survey capability and high-cadenced observations, is a great tool to study the variable universe. &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/feature/goddard/2019/nasa-s-tess-mission-spots-its-1st-star-shredding-black-hole/"&gt;TESS watched a star being torn apart by a black hole in a phenomenon known as a tidal disruption event (TDE)&lt;/a&gt;. This event was named ASASSN-19bt as it was first identified by the ground-based All-Sky Automated Survey for Supernovae. The data provided by TESS allowed the astronomical community to view the light from the event much closer to the black hole than ever before!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TESS has also been used to create detailed high-cadenced light curves of supernovae (SNe). &lt;a href="https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2019arXiv190402171F/abstract"&gt;Recent work presented 18 early time light curves of Type Ia SNe occurring in the first six sectors of TESS data&lt;/a&gt;. SN Ia are one of our most mature cosmological probes, however we still do not have a firm understanding of the progenitor systems. The detailed early time observations of these transient events by TESS are extremely important and can provide vital information in understanding these systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The science highlighted here represents only a small amount of the incredible science to have come out of the TESS prime mission to date, thanks to efforts of both the TESS mission team and the TESS community. So what is next for TESS? The two-year prime mission will end in July 2020, and given the success of TESS, the mission has now been extended for a further two years through October 2022. TESS will remain as NASA's key planet hunter, but it will also continue to provide the high-quality wide-field survey data required for the exploration of many different kinds of variable and transient events in the night sky -- part of which is shown below in the &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/feature/goddard/2019/nasa-s-tess-presents-panorama-of-southern-sky/"&gt;mosaic of the southern sky as seen by TESS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:70%;" src="images/TESS_south_hires_azeq_no_labels_800.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>New Support Scientist on the GI team</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/new-support-scientist-on-the-gi-team.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-04-16T12:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-04-16T12:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Rebekah Hounsell, Knicole Colon</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2020-04-16:/docs/tess/new-support-scientist-on-the-gi-team.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Dr. Rebekah Hounsell recently started a new position with the TESS GI team as a support scientist. She holds a joint position as an associate research scientist at the University of Maryland, Baltimore County. She joined the team from the University of Pennsylvania where she was a postdoctoral researcher contributing …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Dr. Rebekah Hounsell recently started a new position with the TESS GI team as a support scientist. She holds a joint position as an associate research scientist at the University of Maryland, Baltimore County. She joined the team from the University of Pennsylvania where she was a postdoctoral researcher contributing to the design of the WFIRST mission and studying supernovae in the Dark Energy Survey. Her doctoral research was performed at Liverpool John Moores University in the UK where she focused on the outbursts and environments of novae. Dr. Hounsell’s research interests are focused on the transient sky and vary in energy range from novae to supernovae, tidal disruption events and gamma-ray bursts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Record number of TESS GI proposals received</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/record-number-of-tess-gi-proposals-received.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-02-21T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-02-21T12:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2020-02-21:/docs/tess/record-number-of-tess-gi-proposals-received.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Guest Investigator program Cycle 3 closed in January. We received a record number of proposals in Cycle 3, which is the first extended mission cycle. A total of 155 proposals were submitted, these a mix of Small, Large, and Key Project proposals. The proposals are currently under review …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Guest Investigator program Cycle 3 closed in January. We received a record number of proposals in Cycle 3, which is the first extended mission cycle. A total of 155 proposals were submitted, these a mix of Small, Large, and Key Project proposals. The proposals are currently under review. Initial results are expected to be announced in May.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS activities at AAS</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-activities-at-aas.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-12-03T16:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-12-03T16:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Knicole Colon</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2019-12-03:/docs/tess/tess-activities-at-aas.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS team is looking forward to attending the upcoming winter AAS meeting in Honolulu next month. There will be many new science results presented from the prime mission, and we will share plans for the first extended mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TESS team will be there staffing a booth all week …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS team is looking forward to attending the upcoming winter AAS meeting in Honolulu next month. There will be many new science results presented from the prime mission, and we will share plans for the first extended mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TESS team will be there staffing a booth all week and serving as a live helpdesk for all your TESS-related questions. In addition, be sure to join us during our evening splinter session on Monday, January 6 starting at 5:30pm, which will feature new science results from the prime mission and a preview of the extended mission. You are also invited to attend our two special sessions taking place on Sunday, January 5 at 2:00pm and Wednesday, January 8 at 2:00pm to hear even more about the latest science from TESS. In addition, you can stop by the NASA traveling Hyperwall on Tuesday, January 7 and Wednesday, January 8, when team members will present additional science highlights from TESS. There will also be a press panel focusing on new science results from TESS, as well as lots of other contributed talks on TESS science taking place during the conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hope you can join us at one or more of these activities! A summary of the TESS activities at AAS 235 is below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;b&gt; Sunday, January 5&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special Session 2:00 pm - 3:30 pm (Room 318A) &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt; 157. Transient Science with TESS &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Owing to its unique observing strategy, the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) has the potential to open new windows on transient science. This session will highlight recent results of TESS data used to study transients, and discuss synergies of TESS with current and future time domain surveys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2:00-2:10pm Michael Fausnaugh (MIT) - &lt;i&gt;TESS and Transients Discovered from the Ground&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2:10-2:20pm Thomas Prince (Caltech) - &lt;i&gt;     The ZTF survey of the TESS fields &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2:20-2:30pm V. Ashley Villar (Harvard) - &lt;i&gt;  Constraining Type Ia Supernova Progenitors Through High-Cadence, Optical Light Curves &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2:30-2:40pm Anna Payne (IfA) - &lt;i&gt; TESS and AGN multi-wavelength variability &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2:40-2:50pm Soichiro Hattori (NYU Abu Dhabi) - &lt;i&gt;    TESS-CPM: A Python package for Background-Corrected Difference Imaging with TESS Full Frame Images &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2:50-3:00pm Patrick Vallely (OSU) - &lt;i&gt; Using TESS and SALT to Understand the Unusual Type Ia ASASSN-18tb &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3:00-3:10pm Thomas Holoien (Carnegie Observatories) - &lt;i&gt;     ASASSN-19bt: The First Tidal Disruption Event Observed with TESS &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3:10-3:20pm Elias Aydi (MSU) - &lt;i&gt;    Novae observations with TESS might change our understanding of explosive transients &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3:20-3:30pm Dheeraj Pasham (MIT) - &lt;i&gt;    Blind searches for rapid transients in TESS FFIs &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;b&gt; Monday, January 6&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Splinter Session 5:30 pm - 7:00 pm (Room 306AB) &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt; NASA's TESS Mission- Exoplanets, Time Domain Astronomy and Astrophysics from the Prime Mission, and Extended Mission Preview &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NASA’s TESS mission launched in 2018, is now well more than halfway through its prime science program, surveying most of the sky, searching for transiting exoplanets orbiting bright, nearby stars. The team has identified well over one thousand promising planet candidates, and an active follow-up program has led to the confirmation of dozens of planets. While the main science goal is measuring the masses of fifty planets smaller than 4 Earth radii, the high-precision long-timeline, high-cadence photometry provided by the TESS cameras allows a wealth of additional astrophysics investigations. A robust Guest Investigator Program complements the exoplanet investigation underway by the TESS Science Team. This splinter session will present mission status, early science results, and future plans for the TESS extended mission, which begins in July 2020. Come join TESS project staff, who will be on hand to answer questions and chat in the informal reception to follow a few brief talks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;b&gt; Tuesday, January 7&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hyperwall Talks (NASA/SMD booth) &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9:40-9:55am Natalia Guerrero (MIT) - &lt;i&gt; Exploring New Planets with TESS &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:45-2:00pm TBD - &lt;i&gt; TBD &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;b&gt; Wednesday, January 8&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hyperwall Talks (NASA/SMD booth) &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9:25-9:40am Laura Vega (NASA GSFC/Vanderbilt University) - &lt;i&gt; Astrophysics with TESS &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;b&gt; Wednesday, January 8&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special Session 2:00 pm - 3:30 pm (Room 323B) &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt; 445. TESS and the Mass/Radius Diagram for Exoplanets &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A striking result from the Kepler mission is that the population of planets orbiting solar-type stars is dominated by planets smaller than 4 Earth radii, with a dip in the occurrence rate near 1.8 Earth Radii, often referred to as the radius gap. Are the planets below the gap rocky like the Earth, while the ones above the gap are more like Neptune? One of the primary goals of the TESS mission is to determine masses and radii for at least 50 planets smaller than 4 Earth radii, thus providing bulk densities and surface gravities needed to address this issue. In this Special Session we will highlight the progress towards this goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2:00-2:12pm David Latham (CfA | Harvard &amp;amp; Smithsonian) - &lt;i&gt;  The Legacy of Kepler&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2:12-2:24pm Li Zeng (CfA | Harvard &amp;amp; Smithsonian) - &lt;i&gt;   Theoretical Models on the Mass/Radius Diagram&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2:24-2:36pm Andrew Howard (Caltech) - &lt;i&gt; HIRES Masses for TESS Planets&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2:36-2:48pm Stéphane Udry (Geneva Observatory) - &lt;i&gt;  Masses of Small Planets from HARPS and ESPRESSO&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2:48-3:00pm Johanna Teske (Carnegie Observatories) - &lt;i&gt;  Mass-Radius Updates from the TESS-Magellan PFS Consortium&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3:00-3:12pm Ryan Cloutier (CfA | Harvard &amp;amp; Smithsonian) - &lt;i&gt; Masses for Planets Transiting M Dwarfs&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3:12-3:24pm Samuel Quinn (CfA | Harvard &amp;amp; Smithsonian) - &lt;i&gt; Summary and Future Directions &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Volunteer to review TESS proposals</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/volunteer-to-review-tess-proposals.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-12-03T15:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-12-03T15:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Knicole Colon, Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2019-12-03:/docs/tess/volunteer-to-review-tess-proposals.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS Cycle 3 Guest Investigator (GI) proposals are due January 16, 2020. The in-person peer review is expected to take place in mid-March 2020. We are currently looking for volunteers with expertise in all areas of astrophysics to serve on our review panel. Topics we are particularly interested in recruiting …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS Cycle 3 Guest Investigator (GI) proposals are due January 16, 2020. The in-person peer review is expected to take place in mid-March 2020. We are currently looking for volunteers with expertise in all areas of astrophysics to serve on our review panel. Topics we are particularly interested in recruiting reviewers for are exoplanet science, asteroseismology, stellar activity, binary stars, and supernova observations. The requirements are that (1) you have a PhD or relevant experience (so this opportunity isn't open to graduate students), and (2) you are not intending to PI a TESS Cycle 3 proposal. If you are undecided about submitting a proposal as PI, you are still welcome to volunteer as a reviewer (it's fine if you later choose to submit a proposal, but we would then not invite you to the review). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're interested in serving as a reviewer, you can submit your name, institution, and areas of expertise via &lt;a href="https://goo.gl/forms/p4ZqiTQSEHjbM6nz2"&gt;this form&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Updates on Cycle 3 Guest Investigator Program</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/updates-on-cycle-3-guest-investigator-program.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-12-03T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-12-03T12:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Knicole Colon</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2019-12-03:/docs/tess/updates-on-cycle-3-guest-investigator-program.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://nspires.nasaprs.com/external/solicitations/summary!init.do?solId={21B53A82-2F78-9C26-3CA6-B9FEFE2AF929}&amp;amp;path=open"&gt;TESS Cycle 3 proposal call&lt;/a&gt;
was released in
October. Proposals are due on January 16, 2020 at 4.30pm EST.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We encourage those interested in submitting a proposal to carefully
read the
&lt;a href="https://nspires.nasaprs.com/external/solicitations/summary!init.do?solId={21B53A82-2F78-9C26-3CA6-B9FEFE2AF929}&amp;amp;path=open"&gt;Call for Proposals&lt;/a&gt;
and the information available on our website regarding &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html"&gt;proposing investigations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We remind proposers that …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://nspires.nasaprs.com/external/solicitations/summary!init.do?solId={21B53A82-2F78-9C26-3CA6-B9FEFE2AF929}&amp;amp;path=open"&gt;TESS Cycle 3 proposal call&lt;/a&gt;
was released in
October. Proposals are due on January 16, 2020 at 4.30pm EST.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We encourage those interested in submitting a proposal to carefully
read the
&lt;a href="https://nspires.nasaprs.com/external/solicitations/summary!init.do?solId={21B53A82-2F78-9C26-3CA6-B9FEFE2AF929}&amp;amp;path=open"&gt;Call for Proposals&lt;/a&gt;
and the information available on our website regarding &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html"&gt;proposing investigations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We remind proposers that in Cycle 3, two new observing modes will potentially be
available and collected at &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html#shared-risk-science"&gt;"shared risk"&lt;/a&gt;: 10-minute cadence full-frame images and 20-second
cadence postage stamps. A 2-minute cadence mode will also be available
as in previous cycles. There is also a new Key Project proposal
category, and ground-based observing focused programs are also
solicited. We also emphasize that in the extended mission, all postage stamp targets will be
selected via this Guest Investigator Program or via the &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html#directors-discretionary-targets"&gt;Director's
Discretionary Targets Program&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TESS Cycle 3 observations will be collected during the first year of the extended mission,
running from July 2020 until June 2021. All Cycle 3 fields are in the
Southern Ecliptic Hemisphere. The
&lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/cgi-bin/tess/webtess/wtv.py"&gt;Web TESS Viewing Tool&lt;/a&gt;
has been updated to include the Cycle 3 pointings, so that proposers
can determine when a target is expected to be observed by TESS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proposers may also be interested in the templates we have created to
assist in putting together a proposal. &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html#proposal-templates"&gt;The templates can be found on
our website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proposers requesting short-cadence target slots (either 20-second or
2-minute cadence) need to submit a target list along with the
proposal. Information on &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html#target-table"&gt;how to create a target table&lt;/a&gt; can be found on
our website, which also includes a link to a tutorial provided by the MAST.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any questions regarding proposing to the TESS Cycle 3 call should be
addressed to &lt;a href="tesshelp@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov"&gt;tesshelp@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Update on pointing for Sectors 24, 25, and 26</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/update-on-pointing-for-sectors-24-25-and-26.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-12-03T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-12-03T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Knicole Colon</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2019-12-03:/docs/tess/update-on-pointing-for-sectors-24-25-and-26.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As previously announced, the field-of-view of the TESS camera array was shifted north by 31° with respect to its nominal pointing in Sectors 14, 15, and 16 in order to reduce the impact of scattered light from the Earth and Moon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TESS project has determined that photometry from TESS …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As previously announced, the field-of-view of the TESS camera array was shifted north by 31° with respect to its nominal pointing in Sectors 14, 15, and 16 in order to reduce the impact of scattered light from the Earth and Moon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TESS project has determined that photometry from TESS would further benefit by shifting the pointing of Sectors 24, 25, and 26 as well. These sectors will be observed between April 15, 2020 and July 4, 2020. &lt;a href="status.html"&gt;The status of all TESS sectors and data availability can be found here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tess.mit.edu/observations/"&gt;Additional details on the pointing change can be found at the MIT TESS website&lt;/a&gt; and correspondingly on the &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/observing-technical.html"&gt;Technical Details page of our website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/cgi-bin/tess/webtess/wtv.py"&gt;Web TESS Viewing Tool (WTV)&lt;/a&gt; that is hosted on our website has been updated to reflect the change in pointing for Sectors 24, 25, and 26.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Full-frame image release cadence survey</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/full-frame-image-release-cadence-survey.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-11-06T11:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-06T11:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2019-11-06:/docs/tess/full-frame-image-release-cadence-survey.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS team are exploring options for making TESS full-frame image (FFI) data available more rapidly. To help us plan these activities we would greatly appreciate anyone interested in TESS FFI data to &lt;a href="https://forms.gle/wS5UqUuL7U4TWoiV7"&gt;fill out this short survey&lt;/a&gt;. Our intention is to understand the value of making FFI data available …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS team are exploring options for making TESS full-frame image (FFI) data available more rapidly. To help us plan these activities we would greatly appreciate anyone interested in TESS FFI data to &lt;a href="https://forms.gle/wS5UqUuL7U4TWoiV7"&gt;fill out this short survey&lt;/a&gt;. Our intention is to understand the value of making FFI data available earlier, and whether MAST services and documentation are required at the same time as data is released.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Update on TESS data availability at MAST</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/update-on-tess-data-availability-at-mast.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-11-05T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-05T12:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Knicole Colon</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2019-11-05:/docs/tess/update-on-tess-data-availability-at-mast.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In order to better inform the community of the arrival times of the
TESS data into the archive, the MAST has changed how and when it will
announce the arrival of new TESS data.  A few days before the data
ingest begins, the date will be placed on the
&lt;a href="https://outerspace.stsci.edu/display/TESS/TESS+Holdings+Available+by+MAST+Service"&gt;TESS …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In order to better inform the community of the arrival times of the
TESS data into the archive, the MAST has changed how and when it will
announce the arrival of new TESS data.  A few days before the data
ingest begins, the date will be placed on the
&lt;a href="https://outerspace.stsci.edu/display/TESS/TESS+Holdings+Available+by+MAST+Service"&gt;TESS Holdings page at MAST&lt;/a&gt;,
and MAST will make an announcement on social media (@MAST_News on
twitter).  After ingest begins, one sector of TESS data takes
approximately 20 hours to archive and make available in the MAST
Portal.  Since data files become available immediately after being
archived, during this ingest process the data gradually appear in the
MAST portal and astroquery searches.  After all data are archived,
MAST services such as the bulk downloads, TESScut, and exo.MAST take
another 1-2 days to bring online.  For more information about ingest
and which services are available for each sector, see the
&lt;a href="https://outerspace.stsci.edu/display/TESS/TESS+Holdings+Available+by+MAST+Service"&gt;TESS Holdings at MAST page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we note that users can also "watch" the MAST page to receive updates on the archive holdings by following the instructions given on the MAST site.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Cycle 3 Guest Investigator announcement</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/cycle-3-guest-investigator-announcement.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-10-21T15:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-21T15:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2019-10-21:/docs/tess/cycle-3-guest-investigator-announcement.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are excited to announce that the &lt;a href="https://nspires.nasaprs.com/external/solicitations/summary!init.do?solId={21B53A82-2F78-9C26-3CA6-B9FEFE2AF929}&amp;amp;path=open"&gt;TESS Cycle 3 proposal call&lt;/a&gt; has been released. &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html"&gt;TESS Cycle 3 observations&lt;/a&gt; will be collected during the first year of the extended mission, running from July 2020 until June 2021. All Cycle 3 fields are in the Southern Ecliptic Hemisphere. Please make sure …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are excited to announce that the &lt;a href="https://nspires.nasaprs.com/external/solicitations/summary!init.do?solId={21B53A82-2F78-9C26-3CA6-B9FEFE2AF929}&amp;amp;path=open"&gt;TESS Cycle 3 proposal call&lt;/a&gt; has been released. &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html"&gt;TESS Cycle 3 observations&lt;/a&gt; will be collected during the first year of the extended mission, running from July 2020 until June 2021. All Cycle 3 fields are in the Southern Ecliptic Hemisphere. Please make sure to take a careful look at &lt;a href="https://nspires.nasaprs.com/external/solicitations/summary!init.do?solId={21B53A82-2F78-9C26-3CA6-B9FEFE2AF929}&amp;amp;path=open"&gt;the call&lt;/a&gt; because there are some significant changes from the previous two cycles. Changes include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A new 20-second cadence mode will potentially be available. Once
commissioned, approximately 1,000 target slots per sector will be
available in this mode. Guest Investigator (GI) observations in this
mode will be collected at &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html#shared-risk-science"&gt;"shared risk"&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A 10-fold increase in the number of 2-minute cadence targets is
available to the GI program. More than 15,000 target slots will be
available in each sector; a total of approximately 200,000 target
slots are available in Cycle 3, facilitating very large GI programs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The full-frame image cadence is planned to be reduced from 30
minutes to 10 minutes. This change in cadence will be considered
a "shared risk"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A new Key Project proposal category is available. These programs
have a maximum duration of 27 months. The programs may be
continued into TESS Cycle 4 and may propose to select targets in
both Cycles 3 and 4 (although only Cycle 3 target lists are solicited
at this time)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ground-based observing focused programs are solicited provided
they support the analysis and/or interpretation of TESS data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Large programs and Key Projects have a 5-page limit for the
scientific/technical/management section&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;References are not included in the page limits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Up to 100 ks of Swift time will be available for joint TESS-Swift proposals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starting in Cycle 3, proposals aimed at detecting small planets in
2-minute cadence data are solicited&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposals are due on January 16, 2020 at 4.30pm EST.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>We want your newsworthy results for AAS</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/we-want-your-newsworthy-results-for-aas.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-04T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-04T13:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Knicole Colon</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2019-09-04:/docs/tess/we-want-your-newsworthy-results-for-aas.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS team will be at AAS in January 2020! If you are also attending, and you plan to present TESS results that you think would be of broad interest to the public, &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/media.html"&gt;please submit a media request&lt;/a&gt;. We would love to showcase as many TESS results as possible, but …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS team will be at AAS in January 2020! If you are also attending, and you plan to present TESS results that you think would be of broad interest to the public, &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/media.html"&gt;please submit a media request&lt;/a&gt;. We would love to showcase as many TESS results as possible, but we need time to prepare stories and graphics. Therefore, we ask that if you are interested in having your work promoted, you submit a media request as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Announcement of the TESS Extended Mission</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/announcement-of-the-tess-extended-mission.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-03T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-03T13:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Knicole Colon</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2019-09-03:/docs/tess/announcement-of-the-tess-extended-mission.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After TESS completes its 2-year prime mission in July 2020, TESS will officially be continuing operations as part of an extended mission! TESS will continue scanning the sky in the extended mission for transiting exoplanets and other transients. As part of this extended mission, Guest Investigator proposals will continue to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After TESS completes its 2-year prime mission in July 2020, TESS will officially be continuing operations as part of an extended mission! TESS will continue scanning the sky in the extended mission for transiting exoplanets and other transients. As part of this extended mission, Guest Investigator proposals will continue to be solicited as part of Cycles 3 and 4. As in the prime mission, Guest Investigators will be able to propose to collect 2-minute cadence data for a select number of targets or request funds to analyze full-frame image data. Two major changes in the extended mission are that a new 20-second cadence mode will be available for observations, and the cadence of full-frame images will change from 30-minutes to 10-minutes. Stay tuned for additional details to be posted on our website and in the Cycle 3 call for proposals, which will be released soon. &lt;a href="https://science.nasa.gov/astrophysics/2019-senior-review-operating-missions/"&gt;Reports from the 2019 NASA Senior Review of Operating Missions can be found here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Update on pointing for Sector 16</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/update-on-pointing-for-sector-16.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-02T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-02T13:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Knicole Colon</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2019-09-02:/docs/tess/update-on-pointing-for-sector-16.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS has been successfully conducting observations in the northern ecliptic hemisphere since July 18th. As previously announced, the field-of-view of the TESS camera array was shifted north by 31° with respect to its nominal pointing in Sectors 14 and 15 in order to reduce the impact of scattered light from …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS has been successfully conducting observations in the northern ecliptic hemisphere since July 18th. As previously announced, the field-of-view of the TESS camera array was shifted north by 31° with respect to its nominal pointing in Sectors 14 and 15 in order to reduce the impact of scattered light from the Earth and Moon. After examining Sector 14 data, it has been decided that the pointing for Sector 16 will also be shifted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tess.mit.edu/observations/"&gt;Additional details on the pointing change can be found at the MIT TESS website&lt;/a&gt; and correspondingly on the &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/observing-technical.html"&gt;Technical Details page of our website&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/cgi-bin/tess/webtess/wtv.py"&gt;Web TESS Viewing Tool (WTV)&lt;/a&gt; that is hosted on our website has been updated to reflect the change in pointing for Sectors 14, 15, and 16.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sky coverage maps for Sectors 1-21 are given below in the ecliptic and celestial coordinate systems, with Sectors 14, 15, and 16 shifted north.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:50%;" src="images/PM_ecl_S1-21_16up.png"&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:50%;" src="images/PM_cel_S1-21_16up.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>All TESS Cycle 1 data available at MAST</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/all-tess-cycle-1-data-available-at-mast.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-01T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-01T13:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Knicole Colon</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2019-09-01:/docs/tess/all-tess-cycle-1-data-available-at-mast.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS has officially completed its survey of the southern sky, observing thirteen sectors in the southern ecliptic hemisphere between July 2018 and July 2019. All of the Cycle 1 data are now publicly available at MAST. &lt;a href="https://outerspace.stsci.edu/display/TESS/TESS+Holdings+Available+by+MAST+Service"&gt;Details of the available data can be found at the MAST site.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Update on TESS pointing in Year 2</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/update-on-tess-pointing-in-year-2.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-27T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-27T13:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Knicole Colon</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2019-06-27:/docs/tess/update-on-tess-pointing-in-year-2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS will observe the northern ecliptic hemisphere during the second year of its primary mission. The cameras will be oriented along a line of ecliptic longitude (as they were in Year 1), with that longitude determined by the anti-solar longitude at the mid-point of the sector. For most of Year …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS will observe the northern ecliptic hemisphere during the second year of its primary mission. The cameras will be oriented along a line of ecliptic longitude (as they were in Year 1), with that longitude determined by the anti-solar longitude at the mid-point of the sector. For most of Year 2, the camera array will be oriented such that Camera 4 is centered on the northern ecliptic pole: in this orientation, the southernmost edge of Camera 1 is ~6° from the ecliptic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, for Sectors 14 and 15, scattered light from the Earth and Moon is predicted to be a significant problem in Cameras 1 and 2, reducing the available observing time for exoplanet transits by as much as 75% in those cameras. To reduce the impact of scattered light, the field-of-view of the camera array will be shifted north by 31° with respect to its nominal pointing in Sectors 14 and 15.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the cameras are shifted north, the northern ecliptic pole will be located 7° from the center of camera 3, and the southernmost edge of Camera 1 will be at an ecliptic latitude of ~37°.  In addition, with this shift, the fields-of-view of Cameras 3 and 4 will be observing “on the other side of the pole”, thereby providing additional observations of parts of the sky that would otherwise only be observed in Sectors 20-22.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scattered light from the Earth and Moon is also expected to be a problem in Sectors 25 and 26 and, to a lesser extent, in Sectors 16 and 24.  The scattered light performance in Sectors 14 and 15 will be reviewed before deciding the instrument pointing in these later sectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sky coverage maps for Sectors 1-21 are given below in the ecliptic and celestial coordinate systems.  Two sets of maps are shown below: the upper pair is the sky coverage if Sector 16 is observed at the nominal camera orientation, while the lower pair is the sky coverage if Sector 16 is shifted north.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tess.mit.edu/observations/"&gt;Additional details on TESS observations can be found at the MIT TESS website&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/cgi-bin/tess/webtess/wtv.py"&gt;Web TESS Viewing Tool (WTV)&lt;/a&gt; has been updated to reflect the change in pointing for Sectors 14 and 15.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sectors 14 and 15 shifted north:&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:50%;" src="images/PM_ecl_S1-21.png"&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:50%;" src="images/PM_cel_S1-21.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sectors 14, 15, and 16 shifted north:&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:50%;" src="images/PM_ecl_S1-21_16up.png"&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:50%;" src="images/PM_cel_S1-21_16up.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Upcoming TESS Conferences</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/upcoming-tess-conferences.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-27T12:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-27T12:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Knicole Colon</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2019-06-27:/docs/tess/upcoming-tess-conferences.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The first year of TESS' prime mission will be completed in July, but
the science is just beginning. Two conferences are being held in July
on TESS science, and it is not too late to register for them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is the TASC5/KASC12 workshop, being held in Cambridge, MA …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The first year of TESS' prime mission will be completed in July, but
the science is just beginning. Two conferences are being held in July
on TESS science, and it is not too late to register for them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is the TASC5/KASC12 workshop, being held in Cambridge, MA
from July 22-26. TASC5/KASC12 will be the first meeting where participants have
the opportunity to present analysis and results from asteroseismology
and precision stellar astrophysics of objects in the southern ecliptic
observed by TESS. The workshop will emphasize the most recent results
from TESS, but will also highlight new results from existing data from
the Kepler and K2 missions; the joint meeting is the 5th workshop of
the TESS Asteroseismic Science Consortium and the 12th workshop of the
Kepler Asteroseismic Science Consortium. &lt;a href="http://web.mit.edu/tasc5/index.html"&gt;Additional details about the meeting can be found at its website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second is the TESS Science Conference I, being held in
Cambridge, MA from July 29-August 2. The TESS Science Conference I
will be the first conference dedicated to TESS mission science,
including exoplanets, asteroseismology, stellar binaries, variable
stars, Solar System science (e.g., asteroids and comets),
extragalactic astronomy (e.g., active galactic nuclei and supernovae),
and any other science that can be done with TESS data. The conference
will cover all aspects of the mission, from TESS data analysis,
through follow-up observations, to the impact of discoveries made with
TESS data on theoretical understanding. &lt;a href="https://tsc.mit.edu/"&gt;Additional details about the meeting can be found at its website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A third conference relevant to TESS that is happening later this year from November 4-8 at NASA's Goddard Space
Flight Center is Rocky Exoplanets in the Era of JWST: Theory and
Observation. With its large primary mirror and complement of IR
instrumentation, the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) is poised to
dramatically expand our view of the environments of rocky
exoplanets. JWST will be further aided by the discovery of a new crop
of small planets orbiting nearby low-mass stars and brown dwarfs from
the TESS mission and ground-based surveys, enabling higher precision
measurements over a wider population of potentially rocky worlds. With
these exciting opportunities on the horizon, now is the time to
improve our understanding of what information can be gleaned about
rocky worlds from these future measurements, based on our
understanding of the observations themselves as well as detailed
modeling of the planetary environments that will be
examined. &lt;a href="https://seec.gsfc.nasa.gov/Symposium.html"&gt;Pre-registration is now open at the meeting website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Guest Investigator Program Cycle 2 results available</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/guest-investigator-program-cycle-2-results-available.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-21T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-21T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Knicole Colon</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2019-06-21:/docs/tess/guest-investigator-program-cycle-2-results-available.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The selection of TESS Guest Investigator Program Cycle 2 proposals has been finalized. A &lt;a href="approved-programs.html"&gt;full list of selected programs&lt;/a&gt; is now available. The over-subscription factor for Cycle 2 was slightly higher than in Cycle 1, so that many highly rated programs were not able to be selected for funding. However …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The selection of TESS Guest Investigator Program Cycle 2 proposals has been finalized. A &lt;a href="approved-programs.html"&gt;full list of selected programs&lt;/a&gt; is now available. The over-subscription factor for Cycle 2 was slightly higher than in Cycle 1, so that many highly rated programs were not able to be selected for funding. However, even though a particular program may not have been selected for funding there is still a good chance that it will be either partially for full executed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Target lists for each sector are posted around the time a sector begins. We anticipate posting the target list for Sector 14 within the next few weeks, prior to the start of Sector 14 on July 18. We encourage TESS users to keep an eye on the &lt;a href="approved-programs.html"&gt;approved programs&lt;/a&gt; page to check if targets in a specific program are being observed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS Input Catalog Version 8 (TIC-8) is now available at MAST</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-input-catalog-version-8-tic-8-is-now-available-at-mast.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-18T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-18T13:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Knicole Colon</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2019-06-18:/docs/tess/tess-input-catalog-version-8-tic-8-is-now-available-at-mast.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Input Catalog Version 8 (TIC-8) presented in &lt;a href="https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2019arXiv190510694S/abstract"&gt;Stassun et al. (2019)&lt;/a&gt; was assembled based on the Gaia DR2 catalog, and augmented with data from many additional catalogs to create a full list of point sources and extended sources that could be observed by TESS. The input catalog data …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Input Catalog Version 8 (TIC-8) presented in &lt;a href="https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2019arXiv190510694S/abstract"&gt;Stassun et al. (2019)&lt;/a&gt; was assembled based on the Gaia DR2 catalog, and augmented with data from many additional catalogs to create a full list of point sources and extended sources that could be observed by TESS. The input catalog data are used to determine the physical and observational parameters of many of the TIC stars, including stellar radius, stellar mass, and effective temperature. TIC-8 includes 1.7 billion point sources and about 100 million extended sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TIC-8 is now available at MAST.  This includes access via the &lt;a href="https://mast.stsci.edu/portal/Mashup/Clients/Mast/Portal.html"&gt;MAST portal&lt;/a&gt; and via &lt;a href="https://archive.stsci.edu/tess/tic_ctl.html"&gt;bulk downloads&lt;/a&gt;.  The &lt;a href="https://archive.stsci.edu/tess/"&gt;MAST TESS page&lt;/a&gt; has all the information. Data Release Notes for TIC-8 as well as previous versions of the TIC can be found &lt;a href="https://outerspace.stsci.edu/display/TESS/TIC+and+CTL+Data+Release+Notes+Home+Page"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A visual overview of the input catalogs and methodology used to construct the TIC is shown in the schematic below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:90%;" src="images/giprogram/tic8_overview_figure2.png"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Overview of the photometric catalogs used to construct the TESS Input Catalog (TIC). Yellow arrows depict the order that catalogs are cross-matched and/or merged. The final TIC (TIC-8 as of 2019-06-01) is represented by the green box at the upper right. Image Credit: &lt;a href="https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2019arXiv190510694S/abstract"&gt;Stassun et al. 2019&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS pointing during Year 2</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-pointing-during-year-2.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-05-22T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-22T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2019-05-22:/docs/tess/tess-pointing-during-year-2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;During certain sectors of Year 2, the Earth and/or Moon are very close to or inside the pre-planned fields-of-view of cameras 1 and 2 for long periods, reducing the number of days useful for transit detections by those two cameras to as few as 7-10 days per sector. The …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;During certain sectors of Year 2, the Earth and/or Moon are very close to or inside the pre-planned fields-of-view of cameras 1 and 2 for long periods, reducing the number of days useful for transit detections by those two cameras to as few as 7-10 days per sector. The TESS team is assessing the optimum pointing of the spacecraft during these sectors to reduce the impact of Earth- and moon-light upon transit detections. Planned Year 2 pointings will be posted once finalized.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>HST-TESS Advisory Committee Call for White Papers</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/hst-tess-advisory-committee-call-for-white-papers.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-05-15T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-15T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2019-05-15:/docs/tess/hst-tess-advisory-committee-call-for-white-papers.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The HST-TESS Advisory Committee chartered by the STScI Director invites input from the astronomical community on the use of HST for follow-up observations of TESS exoplanet discoveries, including HST preparatory and supporting observations for JWST follow-up of TESS-discovered planets.  Further information on example topics, format, and white paper authorship can …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The HST-TESS Advisory Committee chartered by the STScI Director invites input from the astronomical community on the use of HST for follow-up observations of TESS exoplanet discoveries, including HST preparatory and supporting observations for JWST follow-up of TESS-discovered planets.  Further information on example topics, format, and white paper authorship can be found at &lt;a href="https://outerspace.stsci.edu/display/HPR/Call+for+White+Papers"&gt;https://outerspace.stsci.edu/display/HPR/Call+for+White+Papers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>ARK/RPS submission page now open</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/arkrps-submission-page-now-open.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-02-18T15:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-18T15:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2019-02-18:/docs/tess/arkrps-submission-page-now-open.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The proposal &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/ark/rps/"&gt;submission page for TESS Cycle 2 proposals&lt;/a&gt; is now open. Proposals are due at 4.30pm eastern time on March 14, 2019. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We welcome proposals addressing compelling scientific questions in almost any area of astrophysics and planetary science. The science motivation may include, but is not limited to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The proposal &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/ark/rps/"&gt;submission page for TESS Cycle 2 proposals&lt;/a&gt; is now open. Proposals are due at 4.30pm eastern time on March 14, 2019. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We welcome proposals addressing compelling scientific questions in almost any area of astrophysics and planetary science. The science motivation may include, but is not limited to, exoplanet characterization, stellar astrophysics, galactic and extragalactic astrophysics, and solar system science.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Guest Investigator Program Cycle 2 deadline now March 14</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/guest-investigator-program-cycle-2-deadline-now-march-14.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-01-31T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-31T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2019-01-31:/docs/tess/guest-investigator-program-cycle-2-deadline-now-march-14.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Due to the partial government shutdown, the TESS Guest Investigator (GI) Program Cycle 2 deadline has been changed. The new Phase-1 due date (via ARK RPS) is 4:30 pm March 14, 2019. At this time we will be soliciting programs that target Northern Ecliptic Hemisphere fields.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS Sessions at the AAS Meeting January 2019</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-sessions-at-the-aas-meeting-january-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-12-21T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-12-21T12:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Knicole Colon</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-12-21:/docs/tess/tess-sessions-at-the-aas-meeting-january-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS team is looking forward to sharing our excitement about the first science results, our high expectations for the two-year science survey, and our plans for the extended mission, at the upcoming winter AAS meeting in Seattle next month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop by our booth in the exhibit hall to find …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS team is looking forward to sharing our excitement about the first science results, our high expectations for the two-year science survey, and our plans for the extended mission, at the upcoming winter AAS meeting in Seattle next month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop by our booth in the exhibit hall to find out how you can access data from the early observation sectors, learn about promising planet candidates, propose new Guest Investigator projects in Cycle 2, and get access to software tools for analyzing target pixel files, light curves and full frame images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be sure to join us for light snacks and beverages during our special evening session on Monday, January 7 starting at 7:00pm, which will feature a mission update, early science results from exoplanet discovery to stellar astrophysics and time domain astronomy, and a Guest Investigator program update. You are also invited to attend our two special sessions taking place on Tuesday, January 8 at 10:00am and Thursday, January 10 at 2:00pm to hear even more about the latest TESS results and plans for exoplanets, stars and transients. Stop by the NASA traveling Hyperwall on Wednesday, January 9, when two team members will present mission overviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please plan to join us at one or more of these activities, and chat with us about how your own TESS research projects are going, and what you’d like to see in the future. A summary of the TESS activities at AAS 233 is below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;b&gt; Monday, January 7&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Splinter Session 7:00 pm - 8:45 pm (Room 201) &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt; NASA's TESS Mission-Early Science from Exoplanets, Time Domain
Astronomy and Astrophysics &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;b&gt; Tuesday, January 8&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special Session 10:00 am - 11:30 am (Room 6A) &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt; 202 TESS: Early Results and Future Plans &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:00-10:15 Roland Vanderspek (Invited) - &lt;i&gt;The Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS): Mission Status and Early Results&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:15-10:30 Jennifer Van Saders (Invited) - &lt;i&gt; Stellar Astrophysics
with TESS &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:30-10:40 David Latham (Invited) - &lt;i&gt; Confirmation and Characterization of TESS Planet Candidates &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:40-10:50 Adina Feinstein - &lt;i&gt; A Complete Survey of the Southern Sky with TESS Full-Frame Images &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:50-11:00 Eric Agol - &lt;i&gt; Exact Model for Phase Curves, Eclipses, and transits of stars and their planets for TESS &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11:00-11:10 Rachel Matson - &lt;i&gt; Speckle Imaging of TESS Host Stars&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11:10-11:20 Derek Buzasi - &lt;i&gt; Extracting Asteroseismology from TESS FFIs: The TASOC Pipeline &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11:20-11:30 Michael Fausnaugh - &lt;i&gt; Transient Science with TESS &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;b&gt; Wednesday, January 9&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hyperwall Talks (NASA/SMD booth) &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9:40-9:55 am TBD - &lt;i&gt; NASA's TESS Mission &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5:15-5:30 pm Tom Barclay - &lt;i&gt; NASA's TESS Mission &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;b&gt; Thursday, January 10&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special Session 2:00 pm - 3:30 pm (Room 6E) &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt; 423 TESS: Early Results and Future Plans II &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2:00-2:10 Joshua Pepper - &lt;i&gt;The Updated TESS Input Catalog and Target Selection&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2:10-2:20 Jon Jenkins - &lt;i&gt;Initial Performance of the TESS Science Pipeline&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2:20-2:30 Natalia Guerrero - &lt;i&gt;TESS Objects of Interest Catalog for Sectors 1-4 of the TESS Mission&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2:30-2:40 Robert Wittenmyer (TBD) - &lt;i&gt;Confirmation of TESS planet candidates with Precise Radial Velocities from MINERVA-Australis&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2:40-2:50 Songhu Wang - &lt;i&gt;HD202772A b: the first confirmation of a Hot Jupiter Discovered by TESS&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2:50-3:00 Johanna Teske - &lt;i&gt; A Southern Hemisphere RV Follow-up Program for TESS with PFS/Magellan&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3:00-3:10 Diana Dragomir - &lt;i&gt; Extending the period range of TESS planet candidates&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3:10-3:20 Steve Howell (TBD) - &lt;i&gt; Resolving the TESS Planet Population with High Resolution Imaging&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3:20-3:30 Maximilian Gunther - &lt;i&gt; The First TESS Re-discoveries of Known Exoplanets&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Sector 1 and 2 data now available at MAST</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/sector-1-and-2-data-now-available-at-mast.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-12-06T14:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-12-06T14:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-12-06:/docs/tess/sector-1-and-2-data-now-available-at-mast.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The first batch of TESS mission data is now available through &lt;a href="http://archive.stsci.edu/tess/"&gt;MAST&lt;/a&gt;. This release includes all data from Sectors 1 and 2, observed between July 25 and September 20, 2018. This includes both FFI and 2-min cadence data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first release of the TESS instrument handbook is also available, as …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The first batch of TESS mission data is now available through &lt;a href="http://archive.stsci.edu/tess/"&gt;MAST&lt;/a&gt;. This release includes all data from Sectors 1 and 2, observed between July 25 and September 20, 2018. This includes both FFI and 2-min cadence data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first release of the TESS instrument handbook is also available, as are data release notes. The details are on our &lt;a href="documentation.html"&gt;documentation page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For an overview of MAST services available for TESS, see their &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/tess_summary"&gt;summary page&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/tess_am"&gt;TESS Archive Manual&lt;/a&gt; details data products, tutorials, and instructions on how to download them from MAST. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Web TESS Viewing Tool updated for Cycle 2</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/web-tess-viewing-tool-updated-for-cycle-2.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-12-04T15:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-12-04T15:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-12-04:/docs/tess/web-tess-viewing-tool-updated-for-cycle-2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The popular tool for determining when a target will be observed by TESS -- &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/cgi-bin/tess/webtess/wtv.py"&gt;Web TESS Viewing Tool (WTV)&lt;/a&gt; -- has been updated to include both year 1 and year 2 of TESS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is an image of the first Cycle 2 sector, showing just camera 3. The Kepler field is overlaid …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The popular tool for determining when a target will be observed by TESS -- &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/cgi-bin/tess/webtess/wtv.py"&gt;Web TESS Viewing Tool (WTV)&lt;/a&gt; -- has been updated to include both year 1 and year 2 of TESS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is an image of the first Cycle 2 sector, showing just camera 3. The Kepler field is overlaid on the image.
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:50%;" src="images/s14c3kepler.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS Sector 1 and 2 data to be available on December 6</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-sector-1-and-2-data-to-be-available-on-december-6.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-12-03T15:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-12-03T15:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-12-03:/docs/tess/tess-sector-1-and-2-data-to-be-available-on-december-6.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS data products from Sectors 1 and 2 will begin to go public starting Thursday December 6 at  9:00 AM US EST. These data will be available at the &lt;a href="https://archive.stsci.edu/tess/summary.html"&gt;MAST archive&lt;/a&gt;. Both Full Frame Images and 2-minute cadence postage stamps will be included in the release.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Data from first two TESS Observation Sectors to be released in early December</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/data-from-first-two-tess-observation-sectors-to-be-released-in-early-december.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-11-19T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-11-19T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Knicole Colon</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-11-19:/docs/tess/data-from-first-two-tess-observation-sectors-to-be-released-in-early-december.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After a successful launch and several months of commissioning, the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) commenced science operations on July 25, 2018. TESS is currently collecting 2-minute cadence and 30-minute cadence full frame image science data from Observation Sector 5 in the Southern ecliptic hemisphere. Data from the first four …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After a successful launch and several months of commissioning, the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) commenced science operations on July 25, 2018. TESS is currently collecting 2-minute cadence and 30-minute cadence full frame image science data from Observation Sector 5 in the Southern ecliptic hemisphere. Data from the first four Observation Sectors have been received on the ground and have been or are being processed through the pipeline. The TESS Science Office has been vetting planet candidates, and has begun issuing public Alerts on a select set of especially promising TESS candidates, that are also being followed up with ground-based telescopes to confirm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is anticipated that the full data set from Observation Sectors 1 and 2 will be released publicly via the Mikulski Archive for Space Telescopes (MAST) in early December 2018. This release will be accompanied by a draft version of the instrument handbook and release notes for each sector. The TESS Data Release Notes will include data quality diagnostics and information about data and instrument characteristics. The full data set from Sectors 3 and 4 will be released no later than January 25, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several services will be available to support the community with this early release of data. A summary of those services that will be available at the MAST for TESS data download of the first two TESS Sectors &lt;a href="http://archive.stsci.edu/tess/summary.html"&gt;is available&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, the MAST will provide an archive manual that will describe an overview of the TESS data products as well as instructions on how to download them.  The manual contains tutorials and python notebooks that walk through how to use the MAST Portal, exo.MAST and Astroquery to retrieve data for scientifically interesting use cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/"&gt;TESS Science Support Center&lt;/a&gt; maintains a list of approved &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/approved-programs.html"&gt;Guest Investigator (GI) programs&lt;/a&gt; and their associated targets that are or will be observed at 2-minute cadence in Cycle 1. The observed GI targets lists are also available for individual sectors. The TESS Science Support Center will provide links to additional tools and tutorials that can be used for analysis of TESS 2-minute cadence Target Pixel Files and 30-minute cadence Full Frame Images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deadline to submit proposals for TESS GI Cycle 2 is February 28, 2019. Cycle 2 covers targets in the Northern ecliptic hemisphere. Further information about the proposal process, proposal tools, and permitted science areas can be found on the TESS Science Support Center website. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://tess.mit.edu/"&gt;TESS website at MIT&lt;/a&gt; contains information regarding the current schedule of observations. Information on how to submit proposals for Director’s Discretionary Targets to be observed at 2-minute cadence in future sectors can also be found at &lt;a href="https://tess.mit.edu/science/ddt/"&gt;the MIT site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questions about the GI program or using TESS data should be sent to &lt;a href="mailto:tesshelp@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov"&gt;the helpdesk&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS Science Support Center is hiring</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-science-support-center-is-hiring.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-11-18T08:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-11-18T08:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-11-18:/docs/tess/tess-science-support-center-is-hiring.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Science Support Center, who run the TESS Guest Investigator Program, are hiring a mission support scientist. The successful applicant will contribute to the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) team, resident within the Astrophysics Sciences Directorate at NASA’s Goddard Space Flight Center. They will primarily be devoted to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Science Support Center, who run the TESS Guest Investigator Program, are hiring a mission support scientist. The successful applicant will contribute to the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) team, resident within the Astrophysics Sciences Directorate at NASA’s Goddard Space Flight Center. They will primarily be devoted to the development of scientific user tools for the TESS Guest Investigator program. Funded under the auspices of the Center for Research and Exploration in Space Science and Technology II (CRESST II), and through the University of Maryland, Baltimore County. Instructions on how to apply are posted to the &lt;a href="https://jobregister.aas.org/ad/7cb1bdeb"&gt;AAS job register&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mission support scientist would have both program support and scientific responsibilities. The scientist would develop software tools to support the TESS GI program, including web-based proposal preparation tools and data analysis tools (e.g., for light curve extraction and modeling). The scientist would also be encouraged to lead as well as contribute to scientific research that utilizes TESS data -- contributing to papers published in scientific journals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applicants must have a Ph.D., or equivalent career experience in Astronomy, Astrophysics, or Computer Science, with interest in high-precision photometric data analysis, time-series analysis, light-curve modeling and/or time-domain astronomy. The applicant must have strong software development skills, familiarity with Python/AstroPy, and GitHub. Excellent collaboration and communication skills, along with demonstrated ability to function well as a member of a team, are essential. Additional experience in a science support role and with web development is desirable but not required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For best consideration submit a Curriculum Vita, list of publications, a 1-2 page statement of experience with supporting scientific research performed by the broader community (e.g., developing software for use by the community or managing an observing program), and contact information for three references by December 3, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Preliminary Target Pixel Files from TESS Object of Interest Alerts Now Public at MAST</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/preliminary-target-pixel-files-from-tess-object-of-interest-alerts-now-public-at-mast.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-04T12:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-10-04T12:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Elisa Quintana</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-10-04:/docs/tess/preliminary-target-pixel-files-from-tess-object-of-interest-alerts-now-public-at-mast.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After completing commissioning and initiating science data collection on July 25th, NASA’s newest planet hunter, the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite, has now completed its first two 27-day science observation sectors and has begun delivering its wealth of data to the ground. The TESS data are being passed through the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After completing commissioning and initiating science data collection on July 25th, NASA’s newest planet hunter, the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite, has now completed its first two 27-day science observation sectors and has begun delivering its wealth of data to the ground. The TESS data are being passed through the mission data pipeline at NASA’s Ames Research Center, referred to as the Science Processing Operations Center (SPOC). The science team has begun sifting through the data, searching for signals that look like promising candidate planets, that they plan to follow up using ground-based and space-based telescopes to confirm. The team began beta-testing the process by which the community is notified of these promising TESS Objects of Interest (TOIs) on September 5th. Announcements of compelling planet candidates have been submitted to preprint servers and await peer review and acceptance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a careful quality check and review of the results by the TESS team, the data for the majority of the Alerts from Sector 1 were deemed ready to share with the broader scientific community. &lt;a href="https://archive.stsci.edu/prepds/tess-data-alerts/"&gt;MAST are hosting the SPOC Target Pixel Files, as well as the light curves and DV reports for those Alerts&lt;/a&gt; for which two-minute cadence data were collected. These data are being made available ahead of the full TESS first data release, and should still be considered preliminary. Short release notes are also available at MAST. Questions can be directed to the helpdesk for the &lt;a href="mailto:tesshelp@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov"&gt;GI program&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS Special Session at Winter AAS</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-special-session-at-winter-aas.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-04T11:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-10-04T11:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Elisa Quintana</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-10-04:/docs/tess/tess-special-session-at-winter-aas.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A Special Session "TESS: Early Results and Future Plans” is scheduled for Tuesday, 8 January, 10:00 AM - 11:30 AM at the winter AAS meeting in Seattle, WA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deadline for regular &lt;a href="https://aas.org/meetings/aas233/abstracts"&gt;abstract submission&lt;/a&gt; of the 233rd AAS meeting to Wednesday, 10 October (9:00 pm ET). The session …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A Special Session "TESS: Early Results and Future Plans” is scheduled for Tuesday, 8 January, 10:00 AM - 11:30 AM at the winter AAS meeting in Seattle, WA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deadline for regular &lt;a href="https://aas.org/meetings/aas233/abstracts"&gt;abstract submission&lt;/a&gt; of the 233rd AAS meeting to Wednesday, 10 October (9:00 pm ET). The session will consist of invited speakers and contributed talks. Due to technical difficulties with the abstract submission system, this session was not appearing in the list of Special Sessions accepting contributed talks. This session is now an option, so we encourage you to consider submitting your abstract to this session (or modifying your submission if you have already submitted). This can be done by selecting the "Special Sessions Accepting Orals" under Session Type, and selecting "TESS: Early Results and Future Plans” under category. Abstracts not selected for the Special Session will go to the general pool of abstracts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also plan to hold a TESS evening Splinter Session and will have an exhibit booth. Stay tuned for more information on these additional TESS activities at AAS. We thank you and look forward to hearing all about your TESS plans and research!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Sector 3 Guest Investigator target lists available</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/sector-3-guest-investigator-target-lists-available.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-09-23T09:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-09-23T09:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-09-23:/docs/tess/sector-3-guest-investigator-target-lists-available.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Targets selected for observations as part of the TESS GI program in Sector 3 are now available. The full list and targets for individual programs is available from the &lt;a href="approved-programs.html#sector-3"&gt;Approved Programs page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Sector 1 data are being processed and validated</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/sector-1-data-are-being-processed-and-validated.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-09-05T15:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-09-05T15:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-09-05:/docs/tess/sector-1-data-are-being-processed-and-validated.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After a successful launch on April 18, 2018, and a series of on-orbit commissioning tasks, NASA’s newest planet hunter, the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite, has completed its first 27-day science observation sector, and has delivered its wealth of data to the ground. TESS is now pointed at the sky …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After a successful launch on April 18, 2018, and a series of on-orbit commissioning tasks, NASA’s newest planet hunter, the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite, has completed its first 27-day science observation sector, and has delivered its wealth of data to the ground. TESS is now pointed at the sky location for the second observation sector of the science survey, and will make a close approach to the Earth and download the first half of data from sector 2 this week. Meanwhile, the Sector 1 data are being passed through data analysis pipelines and the science team has begun sifting through the data, searching for signals that look like promising candidate planets. The TESS team has reported that the mission data have revealed dozens of exciting candidates that they plan to follow up using powerful ground-based telescopes to confirm. The team has begun beta-testing the process by which the community will be notified of these promising "TESS Object of Interest" (TOIs), with the goal of issuing fully public TOI Alerts in the next few months. The selected beta testers include professional and amateur astronomers who will contribute to the TESS exoplanet follow-up process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every new mission goes through a period of data validation and verification before beginning delivery of the final data to a public archive. This serves to test how the pipelines are performing on actual flight data from the mission, and determines whether any changes need to be made before the data are fully prepared for delivery to the archive. In the case of the TESS mission, once the data are delivered to the Mikulski Archive at Space Telescope (MAST) in Baltimore, they will be immediately available to anyone. The first delivery of TESS data to MAST is expected to occur no later than six months from the start of science observations, and will include all data from the first 4 27-day observations sectors. TOI Alerts will allow the broader astrophysics community, and the general public, to follow along with TESS’s most exciting discoveries, even before the first data are available in the MAST archive.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Sector 2 GI target list available</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/sector-2-gi-target-list-available.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-08-27T08:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-08-27T08:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-08-27:/docs/tess/sector-2-gi-target-list-available.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS Sector 2 began last week. The &lt;a href="approved-programs.html#sector-2"&gt;Sector 2 targets are now available&lt;/a&gt; from the GI website. The targets are broken down by individual program, and &lt;a href="status.html"&gt;the full list is available&lt;/a&gt;. TESS Sector 2 will run through September 20.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Changes in the TESS team at Goddard</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/changes-in-the-tess-team-at-goddard.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-08-17T08:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-08-17T08:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-08-17:/docs/tess/changes-in-the-tess-team-at-goddard.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There have been a few changes to &lt;a href="helpdesk.html"&gt;TESS team at Goddard Space Flight Center&lt;/a&gt;. Padi Boyd has replaced Stephen Rinehart as TESS Project Scientist. Stephen has taken up a detail at NASA HQ. Elisa Quintana will be replacing Padi as TESS Deputy Project Scientist. Tom Barclay and Knicole Colón will …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There have been a few changes to &lt;a href="helpdesk.html"&gt;TESS team at Goddard Space Flight Center&lt;/a&gt;. Padi Boyd has replaced Stephen Rinehart as TESS Project Scientist. Stephen has taken up a detail at NASA HQ. Elisa Quintana will be replacing Padi as TESS Deputy Project Scientist. Tom Barclay and Knicole Colón will be leading the TESS Science Support Center, which runs the Guest Investigator Program.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>First TESS downlink successfully completed</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/first-tess-downlink-successfully-completed.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-08-09T08:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-08-09T08:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-08-09:/docs/tess/first-tess-downlink-successfully-completed.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS successfully completed the first downlink of science data on August 8. The data was transmitted via the NASA Deep Space Network. The full orbit work of data took took 1.25 hours to dump 53GB of data. TESS will now complete a second orbit targeting the same field as …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS successfully completed the first downlink of science data on August 8. The data was transmitted via the NASA Deep Space Network. The full orbit work of data took took 1.25 hours to dump 53GB of data. TESS will now complete a second orbit targeting the same field as it did for the previous orbit. The the combination of these two orbits will make-up Sector 1. Sector 2 is due to begin on August 22. These data are planned to be released in January 2019.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Sector 1 preliminary GI target list available</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/sector-1-preliminary-gi-target-list-available.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-08-06T08:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-08-06T08:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-08-06:/docs/tess/sector-1-preliminary-gi-target-list-available.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A preliminary list of targets Sector 1 targets that were requested and observed through the TESS Guest Investigator program &lt;a href="approved-programs.html"&gt;is now available&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, estimated dates for future sectors, and targets for those sectors is available on the &lt;a href="status.html"&gt;status page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have also updated the &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/cgi-bin/tess/webtess/wtv.py"&gt;TESS web tool&lt;/a&gt; to now give …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A preliminary list of targets Sector 1 targets that were requested and observed through the TESS Guest Investigator program &lt;a href="approved-programs.html"&gt;is now available&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, estimated dates for future sectors, and targets for those sectors is available on the &lt;a href="status.html"&gt;status page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have also updated the &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/cgi-bin/tess/webtess/wtv.py"&gt;TESS web tool&lt;/a&gt; to now give a guide on when targets are observable in the first year of the survey.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS Spacecraft Starts Science Operations</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-spacecraft-starts-science-operations.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-07-27T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-07-27T13:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-07-27:/docs/tess/tess-spacecraft-starts-science-operations.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;NASA’s Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite has started its search for planets around nearby stars, officially beginning science operations on July 25, 2018. TESS is expected to transmit its first series of science data back to Earth in August, and thereafter periodically every 13.5 days, once per orbit, as …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;NASA’s Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite has started its search for planets around nearby stars, officially beginning science operations on July 25, 2018. TESS is expected to transmit its first series of science data back to Earth in August, and thereafter periodically every 13.5 days, once per orbit, as the spacecraft makes it closest approach to Earth. The TESS Science Team will begin searching the data for new planets immediately after the first series arrives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have updated our &lt;a href="status.html"&gt;TESS status page&lt;/a&gt; to list the dates when the 13 Southern hemisphere sectors will be observed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>NASA’s TESS spacecraft continues testing prior to first observations</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/nasas-tess-spacecraft-continues-testing-prior-to-first-observations.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-07-11T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-07-11T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Thomas Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-07-11:/docs/tess/nasas-tess-spacecraft-continues-testing-prior-to-first-observations.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After a successful launch on April 18, 2018, NASA's newest planet hunter, the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite, is currently undergoing a series of commissioning tests before it begins searching for planets. The TESS team has reported that the spacecraft and cameras are in good health, and the spacecraft has successfully …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After a successful launch on April 18, 2018, NASA's newest planet hunter, the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite, is currently undergoing a series of commissioning tests before it begins searching for planets. The TESS team has reported that the spacecraft and cameras are in good health, and the spacecraft has successfully reached its final science orbit. he team continues to conduct tests in order to optimize spacecraft performance with a goal of beginning science at the end of July. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every new mission goes through a commissioning period of testing and adjustments before beginning science operations. This serves to test how the spacecraft and its instruments are performing and determines whether any changes need to be made before the mission starts observations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS Input Catalog Updated</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-input-catalog-updated.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-06-22T02:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-06-22T02:01:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Josh Schlieder</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-06-22:/docs/tess/tess-input-catalog-updated.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS mission is pleased to announce the release of the updated version of the TESS Input Catalog and associated documentation. TIC-6 is a compiled catalog of 700 million stars and galaxies across the whole sky.  It includes positions, proper motions, parallaxes, and colors of stars, along with derived physical …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS mission is pleased to announce the release of the updated version of the TESS Input Catalog and associated documentation. TIC-6 is a compiled catalog of 700 million stars and galaxies across the whole sky.  It includes positions, proper motions, parallaxes, and colors of stars, along with derived physical properties of many stars, including temperatures, masses, and radii for several million of the nearest and brightest stars in the sky.  This catalog serves as the basis for selecting TESS exoplanet targets.  A new version of the TIC will be released by the end of 2018 that incorporates additional catalogs, including Gaia Data Release 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A full description of the TIC can be found &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1706.00495"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TIC access is available via the &lt;a href="https://archive.stsci.edu/tess/"&gt;MAST&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Users can work with a subset of the TIC using &lt;a href="https://filtergraph.com/tess_ctl"&gt;Filtergraph&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS successfully completes lunar flyby</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-successfully-completes-lunar-flyby.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-21T02:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-05-21T02:01:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Elisa Quintana</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-05-21:/docs/tess/tess-successfully-completes-lunar-flyby.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS successfully completed a lunar flyby on 17 May at 06:34:35 UTC (2:34 AM EST). At its closest approach, TESS was 8,253 km from the lunar surface. Based on the successful lunar flyby, no adjustment burn was required. The next maneuver is the Period Adjust Maneuver …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS successfully completed a lunar flyby on 17 May at 06:34:35 UTC (2:34 AM EST). At its closest approach, TESS was 8,253 km from the lunar surface. Based on the successful lunar flyby, no adjustment burn was required. The next maneuver is the Period Adjust Maneuver (PAM) on May 30th which will put TESS into its final science orbit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of commissioning, the TESS science team took a 2-second test exposure using one of four TESS cameras, providing an exciting glimpse of the type of image expected from each of TESS’ four cameras. The image is centered on the southern constellation Centaurus with the bright star Beta Centauri visible towards the lower left edge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:67%;" src="images/tess-test-image.png"&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
A science-quality image, taken when the instrument is in fine-point and the cameras are operating at a nominal temperature for science data collection, is expected to be released in June.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/the-tess-space-telescope.html#tess-cameras"&gt;TESS cameras&lt;/a&gt; were developed and built by MIT Lincoln Laboratory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The full resolution image, courtesy of &lt;a href="https://tess.mit.edu"&gt;MIT’s TESS Science Office&lt;/a&gt;, can be found &lt;a href="https://tess.mit.edu/wp-content/uploads/tess-centaurus-field-full-res.jpg"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS commissioning nominal and on track for lunar encounter</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-commissioning-nominal-and-on-track-for-lunar-encounter.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-15T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-05-15T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Joshua Schlieder</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-05-15:/docs/tess/tess-commissioning-nominal-and-on-track-for-lunar-encounter.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS commissioning has been nominal. The space craft has undergone several phasing orbit burns and turn on and checkout of key subsystems. Since launch on April 18, TESS has reached many mission milestones that include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Separation from the Falcon 9 second stage, solar array deployment, and first contact with NASA …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS commissioning has been nominal. The space craft has undergone several phasing orbit burns and turn on and checkout of key subsystems. Since launch on April 18, TESS has reached many mission milestones that include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Separation from the Falcon 9 second stage, solar array deployment, and first contact with NASA TDRS and the NASA Deep Space Network&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Star Trackers turned on, Attitude Control System transitioned to Coarse Pointing Inertial, and attitude thrusters tested&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First Apogee Maneuver successfully completed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Star Tracker and Reaction Wheel Assembly calibration completed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First Perigee Maneuver successfully completed, Ka-band transmitter turned on, Data Handling Unit computer turned on and first data packets transmitted via DSN&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second Apogee Maneuver not performed due to good system performance during first two maneuvers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The four cameras were powered on and began collecting data for calibration&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TESS was placed in Fine Pointing Mode using camera supplied quaternions for first time&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second Perigee Maneuver successfully completed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cameras operating nominally and taking data as they cooled to -85 C&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third Perigee Maneuver successfully completed sending TESS is on its way to the lunar encounter!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lunar encounter will occur at 06:34:35 UTC on May 17th and will bring TESS within 8000 km of the lunar surface and use the Moon’s gravity to change the orbital inclination and send the space craft toward its final science orbit. Science operations are anticipated to begin mid-June.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Three-body dynamics in the TESS orbit</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/three-body-dynamics-in-the-tess-orbit.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-09T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-05-09T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-05-09:/docs/tess/three-body-dynamics-in-the-tess-orbit.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS is making it's way through the phasing orbits, onward to the lunar flyby on May 18. Papers describing the peculiarities and intricacies of the orbit are available in &lt;a href="documentation.html"&gt;papers from 2014 and 2016&lt;/a&gt; on our documentation page. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While in the final science orbit, TESS, like anybody in a three-body …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS is making it's way through the phasing orbits, onward to the lunar flyby on May 18. Papers describing the peculiarities and intricacies of the orbit are available in &lt;a href="documentation.html"&gt;papers from 2014 and 2016&lt;/a&gt; on our documentation page. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While in the final science orbit, TESS, like anybody in a three-body system with little station keeping, goes through &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kozai_mechanism"&gt;Kozai cycles&lt;/a&gt;. TESS will primarily undergo tho periodic oscillations, one on a 10 month cycle, and another with a 10 year cycle. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what does this mean? Well, the orbital period is not constant, neither is the inclination, eccentricity or any of the other orbital parameters. The orbital period ranges from about 12.8 to 14.6 days, with an average of 13.65 days. Furthermore, between now and 2020, the perigee distance will range from about 10 to 20 earth-radii.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The figure below nicely illustrates Kozai cycles influencing the argument of perigee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:67%;" src="images/tess-aop.png"&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Successful TESS launch</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/successful-tess-launch.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-19T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-04-19T13:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-04-19:/docs/tess/successful-tess-launch.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are delighted that TESS was successfully delivered into space on a SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket. TESS launched April 18 at 6:51 p.m. EDT from Cape Canaveral Air Force Station, roughly 40 minutes later TESS separated from the second stage. Shortly after, solar arrays were deployed and telemetry …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are delighted that TESS was successfully delivered into space on a SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket. TESS launched April 18 at 6:51 p.m. EDT from Cape Canaveral Air Force Station, roughly 40 minutes later TESS separated from the second stage. Shortly after, solar arrays were deployed and telemetry indicated this occurred flawlessly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TESS will now undergo a 60 day commissioning plan before beginning the science program.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS launch today!</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-launch-today.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-16T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-04-16T13:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-04-16:/docs/tess/tess-launch-today.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;UPDATE - Now targeting April 18 for launch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TESS will launch aboard a SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket on Monday April 16 at 6:32 pm from Space Launch Complex 40 at Cape Canaveral Airforce Station! The TESS spacecraft has been fueled and encapsulated in the rocket fairing and the Falcon 9 …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;UPDATE - Now targeting April 18 for launch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TESS will launch aboard a SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket on Monday April 16 at 6:32 pm from Space Launch Complex 40 at Cape Canaveral Airforce Station! The TESS spacecraft has been fueled and encapsulated in the rocket fairing and the Falcon 9 that will carry TESS to orbit has undergone a successful static fire. The fairing with TESS inside has been moved to the hangar at pad 40 to be mounted to the rocket. The team has passed the Launch Readiness Review and the are go for launch. In just hours away TESS will begin a 2 year mission to find planets orbiting the closest and brightest stars!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information check out &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/tess/"&gt;nasa.gov/tess&lt;/a&gt; for the latest updates, including links to watch the launch live on Monday, or follow on social media &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/NASAGoddard"&gt;@NASAGoddard&lt;/a&gt; and at &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/NASA_TESS"&gt;@NASA_TESS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Watch the launch</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/watch-the-launch.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-12T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-04-12T13:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-04-12:/docs/tess/watch-the-launch.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS is preparing for launch at 6.32pm EDT on Monday April 16. Update will be posted on the &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/tess"&gt;public affairs website&lt;/a&gt;. Many familiar faces will be appearing on &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/press-release/nasa-television-to-air-launch-of-next-planet-hunting-mission"&gt;NASA TV this coming Sunday and Monday&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can watch the launch live at &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/tess"&gt;nasa.gov/tess&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS simulated data available</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-simulated-data-available.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-01T02:01:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-03-01T02:01:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Elisa Quintana</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-03-01:/docs/tess/tess-simulated-data-available.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS simulated data is now available to the public at the &lt;a href="http://archive.stsci.edu/tess/ete-6.html"&gt;MAST's TESS data page&lt;/a&gt;. There you will find information on the data products, how the data products were created, and how to access the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simulated data, called ETE-6 (End-To-End 6) was created by TESS team members from …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS simulated data is now available to the public at the &lt;a href="http://archive.stsci.edu/tess/ete-6.html"&gt;MAST's TESS data page&lt;/a&gt;. There you will find information on the data products, how the data products were created, and how to access the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simulated data, called ETE-6 (End-To-End 6) was created by TESS team members from NASA Ames and MIT to test the TESS ground system. This synthetic data contains 1 sector (slightly longer than two orbits) of TESS data and is meant to reflect what the archival data products will look like when produced for actual flight data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ETE-6 includes samples of the following data products:
Uncalibrated FFI's
Calibrated FFI's 
Extracted Light Curves (The simulated 2-min cadence data consist of 20,610 cadences)
Target Pixel Files
Data Validation Files 
Cotrending Basis Vectors 
Collateral Target Pixel Files
Models (Huffman tables, Mean Black table, flat-field, read-noise, linearity, gain, etc.) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data inlude injected signals to mimic transiting planets, eclipsing binaries, and stellar variability in 15,000 target stars selected for 2-minute cadence observations. Note these injected signals were designed to test the sensitivity of the NASA Ames planet search pipeline and does not represent what is expected in the actual data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://archive.stsci.edu/missions/tess/ete-6/ETE-6_README.pdf"&gt;README&lt;/a&gt; file is available at MAST and contains information on how these products were created and their caveats. More detailed information on the data products can be found in the &lt;a href="https://archive.stsci.edu/missions/tess/doc/EXP-TESS-ARC-ICD-TM-0014.pdf"&gt;TESS Science Data Products Description&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These data will allow the astronomical community to develop software and tools, and follow-up observation strategies, in anticipation for actual data, which is expected to be delivered to the MAST within 6 months of the start of science operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More information on TESS can be found at the &lt;a href="https://archive.stsci.edu/tess/"&gt;MAST TESS homepage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS arrives at Kennedy Space Center and updated launch date</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-arrives-at-kennedy-space-center-and-updated-launch-date.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-15T02:01:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-15T02:01:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Elisa Quintana</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-02-15:/docs/tess/tess-arrives-at-kennedy-space-center-and-updated-launch-date.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS has been transported from Orbital ATK in Dulles, VA, to Kennedy Space Center where it will be &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/feature/goddard/2018/nasa-s-transiting-exoplanet-survey-satellite-arrives-at-kennedy-space-center-for-launch"&gt;prepped for launch&lt;/a&gt;. Over the next month, the spacecraft will be prepped for launch at Kennedy’s Payload Hazardous Servicing Facility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Launch will be on a SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket from Cape …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS has been transported from Orbital ATK in Dulles, VA, to Kennedy Space Center where it will be &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/feature/goddard/2018/nasa-s-transiting-exoplanet-survey-satellite-arrives-at-kennedy-space-center-for-launch"&gt;prepped for launch&lt;/a&gt;. Over the next month, the spacecraft will be prepped for launch at Kennedy’s Payload Hazardous Servicing Facility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Launch will be on a SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket from Cape Canaveral Air Force Station nearby NASA’s Kennedy Space Center in Florida. The launch will be no earlier than April 16, pending range approval.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:67%;" src="images/tess-at-ksc.jpg"&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS Highlights at AAS 231</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-highlights-at-aas-231.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-29T02:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-29T02:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Elisa Quintana</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-01-29:/docs/tess/tess-highlights-at-aas-231.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS team members and scientists participated in a number of successful events at the &lt;a href="https://aas.org/meetings/aas231"&gt;231st American Astronomical Society&lt;/a&gt; meeting in National Harbor, MD, in January 2018. &lt;a href="tess-team-at-aas-231.html"&gt;TESS activities&lt;/a&gt; included a joint evening splinter session on NASA's TESS and K2 missions, a special seminar for science writers, and a number of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS team members and scientists participated in a number of successful events at the &lt;a href="https://aas.org/meetings/aas231"&gt;231st American Astronomical Society&lt;/a&gt; meeting in National Harbor, MD, in January 2018. &lt;a href="tess-team-at-aas-231.html"&gt;TESS activities&lt;/a&gt; included a joint evening splinter session on NASA's TESS and K2 missions, a special seminar for science writers, and a number of talks, posters, and hyperwall presentations. Team members from MIT and NASA Goddard were also on hand to answer questions about the mission and feasibility of planned observations at a TESS booth in the exhibition hall, and there was much excitement for the upcoming launch throughout the meeting. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A special &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/sites/default/files/atoms/files/tesssciencewritersguidedraft23.pdf"&gt;TESS Science Writers Guide&lt;/a&gt; was out together &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:67%;" src="images/science-writers-guide.png"&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
TESS Science Writer's Guide available in PDF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:67%;" src="images/diana-hyperwall.jpg"&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
NASA Hyperwall Stories: Finding New Worlds with the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite, Diana Dragomir (MIT)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:67%;" src="images/michael-hyperwall.jpg"&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
NASA Hyperwall Stories: TESS Mission Overview, Michael Fasnaugh (MIT)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:67%;" src="images/stephen-hyperwall.jpg"&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
NASA Hyperwall Stories: TESS Guest Investigator Program, Stephen Rinehart (NASA GSFC)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:67%;" src="images/aas231 - booth.jpg"&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
TESS team members staffing the TESS Booth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:67%;" src="images/aas231 - booth2.jpg"&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
TESS team members staffing the TESS Booth.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Guest Investigator Program Cycle 1 results available</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/guest-investigator-program-cycle-1-results-available.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-25T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-25T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-01-25:/docs/tess/guest-investigator-program-cycle-1-results-available.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The selection of TESS Guest Investigator Program Cycle 1 proposals has been finalized. A &lt;a href="approved-programs.html"&gt;full list of selected programs&lt;/a&gt; is available. TESS is scheduled to launch by the end of March. If this schedule holds, science operation will begin at the start of June, with the first data reaching &lt;a href="http://archive.stsci.edu/tess"&gt;the …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The selection of TESS Guest Investigator Program Cycle 1 proposals has been finalized. A &lt;a href="approved-programs.html"&gt;full list of selected programs&lt;/a&gt; is available. TESS is scheduled to launch by the end of March. If this schedule holds, science operation will begin at the start of June, with the first data reaching &lt;a href="http://archive.stsci.edu/tess"&gt;the archive&lt;/a&gt; at the beginning of December. Grants will be released when data is publicly available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The over-subscription factor for this program was extremely high (4.5). Many highly rated programs were not able to be selected for funding. However, we have good news. All full-frame-image data will be released publicly with no exclusive use period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, we anticipate that the number of executed 2-minute cadence target programs will significantly exceed the number that we were able to fund. Therefore, even though a particular program may not have been selected for funding there is still a good chance that it will be either partially for full executed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We anticipate that target lists for the first sector to be available within a few weeks of launch. When available, we will make that information available.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS Input Catalog Version 6 (TIC-6) is now online at MAST</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-input-catalog-version-6-tic-6-is-now-online-at-mast.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-23T13:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-23T13:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Elisa Quintana</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-01-23:/docs/tess/tess-input-catalog-version-6-tic-6-is-now-online-at-mast.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Input Catalot Version 6 (TIC-6) is now available at MAST.  This includes access via the &lt;a href="https://mast.stsci.edu/portal/Mashup/Clients/Mast/Portal.html"&gt;MAST portal&lt;/a&gt;, using &lt;a href="http://mastweb.stsci.edu/mcasjobs/"&gt;CasJobs&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://archive.stsci.edu/missions/tess/index.html"&gt;bulk downloads&lt;/a&gt;.  The &lt;a href="https://archive.stsci.edu/tess/"&gt;MAST TESS page&lt;/a&gt; has all the information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The live &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1zdiKMs4Ld4cXZ2DW4lMX-fuxAF6hPHTjqjIwGqnfjqI/edit"&gt;TIC-6 Data Release Notes&lt;/a&gt; provide information on the changes from TIC Version 5 (TIC-5). Documentation on …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Input Catalot Version 6 (TIC-6) is now available at MAST.  This includes access via the &lt;a href="https://mast.stsci.edu/portal/Mashup/Clients/Mast/Portal.html"&gt;MAST portal&lt;/a&gt;, using &lt;a href="http://mastweb.stsci.edu/mcasjobs/"&gt;CasJobs&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://archive.stsci.edu/missions/tess/index.html"&gt;bulk downloads&lt;/a&gt;.  The &lt;a href="https://archive.stsci.edu/tess/"&gt;MAST TESS page&lt;/a&gt; has all the information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The live &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1zdiKMs4Ld4cXZ2DW4lMX-fuxAF6hPHTjqjIwGqnfjqI/edit"&gt;TIC-6 Data Release Notes&lt;/a&gt; provide information on the changes from TIC Version 5 (TIC-5). Documentation on the content of the TIC can be found &lt;a href="https://archive.stsci.edu/missions/tess/doc/tic_v5_drn.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Note this documentation is specific to TIC Version 5 (TIC-5), so please refer to the release notes for the most up-to-date documentation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questions can be sent to our &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/helpdesk.html"&gt;help desk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the TESS Target Selection Working Group and TESS team members for their hard work in making this resource available! Also thanks to Scott Fleming and the team at MAST for supporting the archiving and documentation of the TIC catalogs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS team at AAS 231</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-team-at-aas-231.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-04T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-04T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-01-04:/docs/tess/tess-team-at-aas-231.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS team will are putting on a number of events at this year's &lt;a href="https://aas.org/meetings/aas231"&gt;American Astronomical Society&lt;/a&gt; in National Harbor, MD. In addition to those events the team are putting on, there are numerous talks from scientist excited to get their hands on the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="evening-splinter-session"&gt;Evening splinter session&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NASA's TESS …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS team will are putting on a number of events at this year's &lt;a href="https://aas.org/meetings/aas231"&gt;American Astronomical Society&lt;/a&gt; in National Harbor, MD. In addition to those events the team are putting on, there are numerous talks from scientist excited to get their hands on the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="evening-splinter-session"&gt;Evening splinter session&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NASA's TESS and K2 missions will be hosting an evening splinter session on Tuesday (Jan 9) at 7.30pm in National Harbor Room 7 of the Gaylord Resort and Convention Center. The event will have limited quantities of snacks and drinks available. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:67%;" src="images/AAS NationHarbor-Jan2018_poster-Spl-K2_TESS.png"&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="hyperwall-talks-at-the-nasa-booth"&gt;Hyperwall Talks at the NASA booth&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="tuesday-january-09-2018"&gt;Tuesday, January 09, 2018&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5:15-5:30 PM, Finding New Worlds with the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite, Diana Dragomir (MIT)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id="wednesday-january-10-2018"&gt;Wednesday, January 10, 2018&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9:35-9:50 AM, TESS Mission Overview, Michael Fasnaugh (MIT)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id="thursday-january-11-2018"&gt;Thursday, January 11, 2018&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9:45-10:00 AM, TESS Guest Investigator Program, Stephen Rinehart (NASA GSFC)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="an-incomplete-list-of-tess-related-talks-and-posters"&gt;An incomplete list of TESS related talks and posters&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="tuesday-january-09-2018_1"&gt;Tuesday, January 09, 2018&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5 id="200-pm-330-pm-national-harbor-11-gaylord-at-national-harbor-128-extrasolar-planets-ii"&gt;2:00 PM-3:30 PM, National Harbor 11 (Gaylord at National Harbor), 128. Extrasolar Planets II&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3:00-3:10 PM 128.06. Simulated JWST/NIRISS Transit Spectroscopy of Anticipated TESS Planets Compared to Select Discoveries from Space-Based and Ground-Based Surveys D. Louie; D. Deming; L. Albert; L. Bouma; J. Bean; M. Lopez-Morales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5 id="530-pm-630-pm-prince-georges-exhibit-hall-gaylord-at-national-harbor-150-computation-data-handling-image-analysis-poster-session"&gt;5:30 PM-6:30 PM, Prince Georges Exhibit Hall (Gaylord at National Harbor), 150 . Computation, Data Handling, Image Analysis Poster Session&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;150.39. Exploring Algorithms for Stellar Light Curves With TESS D. Buzasi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id="wednesday-january-10-2018_1"&gt;Wednesday, January 10, 2018&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5 id="530-pm-630-pm-prince-georges-exhibit-hall-gaylord-at-national-harbor-246-extrasolar-planets-detection-poster-session"&gt;5:30 PM-6:30 PM, Prince Georges Exhibit Hall (Gaylord at National Harbor), 246. Extrasolar Planets: Detection Poster Session&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;246.05. Transit Precovery: Determining Ephemerides for Long-Period TESS Detections with KELT Photometry X. Yao; J. Pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;246.23. Prospects for Ground-Based Detection and Follow-up of TESS-Discovered Exoplanets M. Varakian; D. Deming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;246.31. High-Resolution Spectroscopy at the Wyoming Infrared Observatory: Setting TESS Science on FHiRE H. Jang-Condell; M.J. Pierce; C.A. Pilachowski; H. Kobulnicky; J.N. McLane&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id="thursday-january-11-2018_1"&gt;Thursday, January 11, 2018&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5 id="1000-am-1130-am-maryland-ballroom-a-gaylord-at-national-harbor-303-detection-of-extrasolar-planets-iii"&gt;10:00 AM-11:30 AM, Maryland Ballroom A (Gaylord at National Harbor), 303. Detection of Extrasolar Planets III&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:00-10:10 AM 303.01. Preparing for TESS: Precision Ground-based Light-curves of Newly Discovered Transiting Exoplanets Y. Li; G. Stefansson; S. Mahadevan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5 id="1000-am-1130-am-national-harbor-11-gaylord-at-national-harbor-310-extrasolar-planets-v"&gt;10:00 AM-11:30 AM, National Harbor 11 (Gaylord at National Harbor), 310. Extrasolar Planets V&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:00-10:20 AM 310.02D. Precision Stellar and Planetary Astrophysics with TESS and Gaia D.J. Stevens&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:20-10:30 AM 310.03. Stellar activity for every TESS star in the Southern sky W.S. Howard; N. Law; O. Fors; H.T. Corbett; J. Ratzloff; D. del Ser&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5 id="200-pm-330-pm-national-harbor-7-gaylord-at-national-harbor-ground-based-support-for-nasa-exoplanet-mission-splinter-meeting"&gt;2:00 PM-3:30 PM, National Harbor 7 (Gaylord at National Harbor), Ground Based Support for NASA Exoplanet Mission, Splinter Meeting&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h4 id="friday-january-12-2018"&gt;Friday, January 12, 2018&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5 id="1000-am-1130-am-maryland-ballroom-a-gaylord-at-national-harbor-403-detection-of-extrasolar-planets-iv"&gt;10:00 AM-11:30 AM, Maryland Ballroom A (Gaylord at National Harbor), 403. Detection of Extrasolar Planets IV&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:40-10:50 AM 403.04. The TESS Input Catalog and Selection of Targets for the TESS Transit Search J. Pepper; K.G. Stassun; M. Paegert; R. Oelkers; N.M. De Lee; G. Torres&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:50-11:00 AM 403.05. Maximizing the TESS Mission’s Yield of Long-Period Planets
D. Dragomir; B.S. Gaudi; S. Villanueva; I. Crossfield; X. Huang; I. Ribas; S. Quinn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11:20-11:30 AM 403.08. Simulating the Exoplanet Yield from the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite T. Barclay; J. Pepper; J. Schlieder; E. Quintana&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5 id="100-pm-200-pm-prince-georges-exhibit-hall-gaylord-at-national-harbor-439-extrasolar-planets-late-poster-session"&gt;1:00 PM-2:00 PM, Prince Georges Exhibit Hall (Gaylord at National Harbor), 439. Extrasolar Planets (Late) Poster Session&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;439.07. A PSF photometry tool for NASA's Kepler, K2, and TESS missions J. De Miranda Cardoso; G. Barentsen; C.L. Hedges; M.A. Gully-Santiago; A. Cody; B. Montet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;439.08. TESS Follow-up Observing Program (TFOP) Working Group:A Mission-led Effort to Coordinate Community Resources to Confirm TESS Planets K. Collins; S.N. Quinn; D.W. Latham; J. Christiansen; D. Ciardi; D. Dragomir; I. Crossfield; S. Seager&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;439.09. TESS Data Processing and Quick-look Pipeline M. Fausnaugh; X. Huang; A. Glidden; N. Guerrero&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;439.10. PyKE3: data analysis tools for NASA's Kepler, K2, and TESS missions C.L. Hedges; J. De Miranda Cardoso; G. Barentsen; M.A. Gully-Santiago; A. Cody; T. Barclay; M. Still&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;439.11. TESS Objects of Interest N. Guerrero; A. Glidden; M. Fausnaugh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;439.12. TESS Ground System Operations and Data Products A. Glidden; N. Guerrero; M. Fausnaugh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Proposal submission now closed</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/proposal-submission-now-closed.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-10-09T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-10-09T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-10-09:/docs/tess/proposal-submission-now-closed.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the many people who submitted Cycle 1 TESS GI proposals, we are very pleased with the response. We are now in the proposal of organizing the review of proposals. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We received over 140 proposals for nearly 100,000 unique 2-min cadence targets. About 60% of proposal were stellar …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the many people who submitted Cycle 1 TESS GI proposals, we are very pleased with the response. We are now in the proposal of organizing the review of proposals. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We received over 140 proposals for nearly 100,000 unique 2-min cadence targets. About 60% of proposal were stellar astrophysics investigations (primarily studies of activity and asteroseismology), a third were focused on exoplanets, and the remaining included extragalactic and solar system investigations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We anticipate that we will be oversubscribed by a factor of six in large programs, a factor of four in small programs, and a factor of five for 2-min cadence targets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Release of TESS cool dwarf catalog</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/release-of-tess-cool-dwarf-catalog.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-10-03T09:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-10-03T09:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-10-03:/docs/tess/release-of-tess-cool-dwarf-catalog.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A paper describing efforts to create a catalog of cool dwarf stars for TESS target selection is available on &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1710.00193"&gt;the arXiv&lt;/a&gt;. This release details the stellar properties of dwarf stars cooler than 4000K, with the specific aim to help identify exoplanet search targets to be observed by TESS at 2-min …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A paper describing efforts to create a catalog of cool dwarf stars for TESS target selection is available on &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1710.00193"&gt;the arXiv&lt;/a&gt;. This release details the stellar properties of dwarf stars cooler than 4000K, with the specific aim to help identify exoplanet search targets to be observed by TESS at 2-min cadence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TESS has the opportunity to search tens of thousands of nearby, cool, late K and M-type dwarfs for transiting exoplanets, an order of magnitude more than current or previous transiting exoplanet surveys. This  catalog is incorporated into the &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html#tess-input-catalog-tic"&gt;TESS Input Catalog&lt;/a&gt; and TESS Candidate Target List(proposing-investigations.html#candidate-target-list-ctl).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Target list pointers</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/target-list-pointers.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-26T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-26T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-09-26:/docs/tess/target-list-pointers.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The proposal deadline is just over a week away and many of you are deep into the proposal writing process. Here are two small reminders/requests for target lists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TESS Guest Investigator Cycle 1 is awarding targets in the Southern Ecliptic Hemisphere. Northern Ecliptic targets will be solicited in Cycle …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The proposal deadline is just over a week away and many of you are deep into the proposal writing process. Here are two small reminders/requests for target lists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TESS Guest Investigator Cycle 1 is awarding targets in the Southern Ecliptic Hemisphere. Northern Ecliptic targets will be solicited in Cycle 2. Including targets that can't be observed won't technically impact your proposal - we will just remove them - but it may suggest to reviewers that you haven't done your homework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your target lists should be in priority order. We many choose to award less than the full proposed target list; providing your targets in ranked order enables us to do this. For proposals with very large target lists, we recommend mentioning in the proposal the minimum number of target required to accomplish the scientific goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Cycle 1 proposal deadline change</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/cycle-1-proposal-deadline-change.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-19T15:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-19T15:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-09-19:/docs/tess/cycle-1-proposal-deadline-change.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The deadline for Cycle 1 proposals has been changed to October 6, 2017 at 4:30 pm Eastern time&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give more time to proposers who are without power because of Hurricane Irma, the Phase-1 proposal due date for Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) Guest Investigator Program - Cycle 1 has …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The deadline for Cycle 1 proposals has been changed to October 6, 2017 at 4:30 pm Eastern time&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give more time to proposers who are without power because of Hurricane Irma, the Phase-1 proposal due date for Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) Guest Investigator Program - Cycle 1 has been delayed one week to October 6, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Amendment to the NASA Research Announcement "Research Opportunities in Space and Earth Sciences (ROSES) 2017" (NNH17ZDA001N) has be posted on the &lt;a href="http://nspires.nasaprs.com"&gt;NASA research opportunity homepage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technical questions concerning this program element may be directed to &lt;a href="mailto:patricia.t.boyd@nasa.gov"&gt;Patricia Boyd&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The NASA point of contact for programmatic information is &lt;a href="mailto:martin.still@nasa.gov"&gt;Martin Still&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Release of Web TESS Target Tool</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/release-of-web-tess-target-tool.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-14T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-14T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-09-14:/docs/tess/release-of-web-tess-target-tool.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are delighted to announce the release of the &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/cgi-bin/tess/webtess/wtm.py"&gt;Web TESS Target Tool&lt;/a&gt;. The tool enables potential TESS users to:
* determine whether their targets are observable in TESS Cycle 1
* estimate the noise level on their targets
* calculate a brightness of their targets in the TESS bandpass&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The functionality of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are delighted to announce the release of the &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/cgi-bin/tess/webtess/wtm.py"&gt;Web TESS Target Tool&lt;/a&gt;. The tool enables potential TESS users to:
* determine whether their targets are observable in TESS Cycle 1
* estimate the noise level on their targets
* calculate a brightness of their targets in the TESS bandpass&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The functionality of this tool is also available via command line tools &lt;a href="proposal-tools.html#ticgen"&gt;ticgen&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="proposal-tools.html#tvguide"&gt;tvguide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For comments and questions about this and any other aspects of the Cycle 1 call for proposals, contact us at &lt;a href="mailto:tessgi@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov"&gt;tessgi@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Release of a software tool to calculate TESS magnitudes and noise level</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/release-of-a-software-tool-to-calculate-tess-magnitudes-and-noise-level.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-10T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-10T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-09-10:/docs/tess/release-of-a-software-tool-to-calculate-tess-magnitudes-and-noise-level.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are pleased to announce the release of a software tool known as &lt;a href="proposal-tools.html#ticgen"&gt;ticgen&lt;/a&gt; that an be used to calculate TESS magnitudes from various different bandpasses, and also calculates the TESS noise level for different brightness sources. The software is a command line tool and can be downloaded from our …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are pleased to announce the release of a software tool known as &lt;a href="proposal-tools.html#ticgen"&gt;ticgen&lt;/a&gt; that an be used to calculate TESS magnitudes from various different bandpasses, and also calculates the TESS noise level for different brightness sources. The software is a command line tool and can be downloaded from our &lt;a href="https://github.com/tessgi/ticgen"&gt;Github site&lt;/a&gt;, where we also provide more information. Both ticgen and our other software &lt;a href="proposal-tools.html#tvguide"&gt;tvguide&lt;/a&gt; can be used to aid users in writing proposals. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, we will soon be released a Web tool that combines the functionality of ticgen and &lt;a href="https://github.com/tessgi/tvguide"&gt;tvguide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Increase in target allocation for GI Program</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/increase-in-target-allocation-for-gi-program.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-09T11:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-09T11:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-09-09:/docs/tess/increase-in-target-allocation-for-gi-program.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The allocation of targets assigned to the Guest Investigator Program in Cycle 1 has been increased from 10,000 to 20,000 targets. Targets will be approximately evenly split over each of the 13 sectors, leading to around 1,500 targets per sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary aim of this increase is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The allocation of targets assigned to the Guest Investigator Program in Cycle 1 has been increased from 10,000 to 20,000 targets. Targets will be approximately evenly split over each of the 13 sectors, leading to around 1,500 targets per sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary aim of this increase is to increase the flexibility that large programs have in their target selection. With this increase in mind, we encourage wide-ranging investigations to consider how they might utilize this increase in available resources.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS to observe bright stars at 2-min cadence</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-to-observe-bright-stars-at-2-min-cadence.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-09T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-09T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-09-09:/docs/tess/tess-to-observe-bright-stars-at-2-min-cadence.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS team has been working together to plan how to merge lists of targets are that are to be observed at two-minute cadence. As a result of these discussions the mission is committing to observing at two-minute cadence all stars that fall into the TESS field of view that …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS team has been working together to plan how to merge lists of targets are that are to be observed at two-minute cadence. As a result of these discussions the mission is committing to observing at two-minute cadence all stars that fall into the TESS field of view that are (a) brighter than 6th magnitude in the TESS bandpass, and (b) but are not too bright that their saturation bleed cannot be captured fully with a pixel mask. For Cycle-1 this accounts for approximately 6,000 stars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have made a slight modification to the &lt;a href="data/core-science-targets-v2.csv"&gt;list of targets&lt;/a&gt; that should not be included in TESS Cycle 1 GI proposals to search for transiting exoplanets using two-minute cadence data. This list now includes these 6,000 bright stars. This change is unlikely to significantly impact any proposals because these the majority of these bright stars are large (M-giants, B-stars, etc.). This makes detecting transiting planets challenging, and the detectability is unlikely to be improved with two-minute cadence over the full-frame image data.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS-HERMES catalog of spectroscopic stellar parameters is now available</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-hermes-catalog-of-spectroscopic-stellar-parameters-is-now-available.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-24T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-24T13:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Elisa Quintana</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-08-24:/docs/tess/tess-hermes-catalog-of-spectroscopic-stellar-parameters-is-now-available.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A catalog of spectroscopic stellar parameters for stars in the TESS southern continuous viewing zone (CVZ) is now available and may prove a useful resource for &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html"&gt;TESS GI proposal preparation&lt;/a&gt;. Data taken by the High Efficiency and Resolution Multi-Element Spectrograph (HERMES) at the Anglo-Australian Telescope, as part of the TESS-HERMES …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A catalog of spectroscopic stellar parameters for stars in the TESS southern continuous viewing zone (CVZ) is now available and may prove a useful resource for &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html"&gt;TESS GI proposal preparation&lt;/a&gt;. Data taken by the High Efficiency and Resolution Multi-Element Spectrograph (HERMES) at the Anglo-Australian Telescope, as part of the TESS-HERMES survey, provides temperature, surface gravity, and metalicity for about 16,000 dwarf and subgiant stars with magnitudes 10&amp;lt;V&amp;lt;13.1, along with Bayesian estimates of stellar properties (distance, extinction, mass, radius, and age) using theoretical isochrones. Stellar surface gravity and radius are made available for an additional set of roughly 8,500 red giants. The TESS-HERMES catalog has identified over a hundred cool dwarfs that were flagged as giant stars in the TESS Input Catalog (TIC).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.physics.usyd.edu.au/tess-hermes/"&gt;TESS-HERMES survey website&lt;/a&gt;  provides links to the catalog (.csv and .fits) and tables describing the content of the catalogs. An article describing the survey (Sharma et al. 2017) can be found &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1707.05753"&gt;on the arxiv&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We thank Sanjib Sharma, Dennis Stello, and the HERMES team for their hard work in making this resource available in time for GI Cycle 1.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Cycle 1 proposal template available</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/cycle-1-proposal-template-available.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-08T15:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-08T15:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-08-08:/docs/tess/cycle-1-proposal-template-available.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE: the proposal deadline has been changed to October 6, 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have made available a &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html#proposal-templates"&gt;Microsoft Word format proposal template&lt;/a&gt;. The aim of creating this is to aid in preparing the proposal document and avoiding compliance issue. There is no requirement to use this template.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a reminder, proposals …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE: the proposal deadline has been changed to October 6, 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have made available a &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html#proposal-templates"&gt;Microsoft Word format proposal template&lt;/a&gt;. The aim of creating this is to aid in preparing the proposal document and avoiding compliance issue. There is no requirement to use this template.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a reminder, proposals should include a Science/Technical/Management section that does not exceed 4-pages long. This page limit includes references and figures. The proposals are due on September 29, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Update: we have also made available &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html#proposal-templates"&gt;Latex and PDF version of the template&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS Guest Investigator Cycle 1 proposal submission page open</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-guest-investigator-cycle-1-proposal-submission-page-open.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-08T14:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-08T14:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-08-08:/docs/tess/tess-guest-investigator-cycle-1-proposal-submission-page-open.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;You can now submit TESS Cycle 1 proposals via the HEASARC's &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/ark/rps/"&gt;Remote Proposal System&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few things to note are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven't used ARK/RPS before, get an account now (it's easy, but don't wait till the last minute)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure your co-I's countries and institutions are recognized by …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;You can now submit TESS Cycle 1 proposals via the HEASARC's &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/ark/rps/"&gt;Remote Proposal System&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few things to note are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven't used ARK/RPS before, get an account now (it's easy, but don't wait till the last minute)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure your co-I's countries and institutions are recognized by ARK - if not, ask them to be added to our list now&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You must "verify" the form, and pass the checks, before you can submit your proposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can discard/modify submitted proposals up until the deadline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're asking for 2-min data, note that there are two different ways to provide your target list: Into the RPS target form itself, or as a separate CSV file upload - the latter will only become possible after you submit your RPS form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS Passes Critical Review</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-passes-critical-review.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-07T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-07T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-08-07:/docs/tess/tess-passes-critical-review.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;NASA's Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) has moved one step closer to launch after &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/feature/goddard/2017/nasa-s-transiting-exoplanet-survey-satellite-passes-critical-review"&gt;successfully passing its Systems Integration Review (SIR)&lt;/a&gt;, an independent review from independent technical and scientific experts who have deemed the mission ready to begin installation of its scientific instrument onto the spacecraft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that TESS has …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;NASA's Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) has moved one step closer to launch after &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/feature/goddard/2017/nasa-s-transiting-exoplanet-survey-satellite-passes-critical-review"&gt;successfully passing its Systems Integration Review (SIR)&lt;/a&gt;, an independent review from independent technical and scientific experts who have deemed the mission ready to begin installation of its scientific instrument onto the spacecraft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that TESS has completed this critical review, the mission's cameras and science data processing computer are scheduled to begin installation onto the spacecraft at Orbital ATK in Dulles, Virginia, over the next several weeks. Once successfully integrated, the spacecraft will spend the rest of the year undergoing rigorous testing to ensure the mission can withstand the harsh environment of space. The spacecraft is scheduled to ship in February to NASA's Kennedy Space Center in Florida for launch aboard a SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the Kepler telescope, by design there is a range of focus and image quality across the TESS camera's field of view. Recent measurements revealed the TESS cameras to have slightly reduced focus and image quality near the outer edge of the image when placed in the cold temperatures of space, and better camera focus and image quality towards the center of the image. The difference between the designed and measured focus and image quality will not affect the mission's science goals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Error in a small number of TIC v5 surface gravities</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/error-in-a-small-number-of-tic-v5-surface-gravities.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-01T14:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-01T14:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-08-01:/docs/tess/error-in-a-small-number-of-tic-v5-surface-gravities.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The surface gravities reported in column 67 of the TESS Input Catalog version 5 (TIC-5), do not accurately represent the expected surface gravities using the reported values for mass (column 73) and radii (column 71). This only affects stars where the stellar properties were calculated using available parallax information (the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The surface gravities reported in column 67 of the TESS Input Catalog version 5 (TIC-5), do not accurately represent the expected surface gravities using the reported values for mass (column 73) and radii (column 71). This only affects stars where the stellar properties were calculated using available parallax information (the stellar properties flag is set to "plx" in column 64 and no other quantities in the TIC are affected. TIC users can either calculate the surface gravity using the provided mass and radius values, or use a &lt;a href="http://archive.stsci.edu/missions/tess/catalogs/tic_v5/tic5_logg_fix.csv"&gt;provided data file&lt;/a&gt; to access the appropriately calculated values. This fix will be built in to the next version of the TIC, version 6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, for TIC v5, numerical columns with values of exactly 0 are actually null values. Starting in TIC v6, these will be properly set to null, but due to a translation error they have been assigned values of exactly 0 in TIC v5 at MAST.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up to date TIC information is available from the &lt;a href="http://archive.stsci.edu/tess/tic_doc.html"&gt;MAST TIC documentation page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>ExoFOP-TESS now online</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/exofop-tess-now-online.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-01T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-01T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Elisa Quintana</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-08-01:/docs/tess/exofop-tess-now-online.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://exofop.ipac.caltech.edu/tess/"&gt;ExoFOP-TESS&lt;/a&gt; is a web-based service developed and operated by the &lt;a href="http://nexsci.caltech.edu"&gt;NASA Exoplanet Science Institute&lt;/a&gt; (NExScI) and the &lt;a href="https://exoplanetarchive.ipac.caltech.edu"&gt;NASA Exoplanet Archive&lt;/a&gt; to optimize resources and facilitate collaboration in follow-up studies of targets observed by TESS. &lt;a href="https://exofop.ipac.caltech.edu"&gt;ExoFOP&lt;/a&gt; serves as a repository for community-gathered follow-up data by allowing upload and display of data …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://exofop.ipac.caltech.edu/tess/"&gt;ExoFOP-TESS&lt;/a&gt; is a web-based service developed and operated by the &lt;a href="http://nexsci.caltech.edu"&gt;NASA Exoplanet Science Institute&lt;/a&gt; (NExScI) and the &lt;a href="https://exoplanetarchive.ipac.caltech.edu"&gt;NASA Exoplanet Archive&lt;/a&gt; to optimize resources and facilitate collaboration in follow-up studies of targets observed by TESS. &lt;a href="https://exofop.ipac.caltech.edu"&gt;ExoFOP&lt;/a&gt; serves as a repository for community-gathered follow-up data by allowing upload and display of data and derived astrophysical parameters, and has been widely used by the Kepler and K2 Follow-Up Observation Programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the initial release of &lt;a href="https://exofop.ipac.caltech.edu/tess/"&gt;ExoFOP-TESS&lt;/a&gt;, overview pages for each of the 10.8 million stars in the &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html#candidate-target-list-ctl"&gt;TESS Candidate Target list (CTL)&lt;/a&gt; have been created. These pages contain data from the TESS Input Catalog (TIC) Version 5, including coordinates, magnitudes, stellar parameters, and planet parameters (if available). The pages also contain external links to other archives, and all content can be viewed without logging in. The ability to upload data and parameters and to search the CTL targets will be coming soon. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See our &lt;a href="followup.html#exoplanet-follow-up-observing-program-exofop"&gt;ExoFOP-TESS&lt;/a&gt; page for more details.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS Guest Investigator Cycle 1 released</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-guest-investigator-cycle-1-released.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-29T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-06-29T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-06-29:/docs/tess/tess-guest-investigator-cycle-1-released.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE: the proposal deadline has been changed to October 6, 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://nspires.nasaprs.com/external/solicitations/summary.do?method=init&amp;amp;solId={7136D288-E4F8-8657-F280-6A4318467883}&amp;amp;path=open"&gt;Cycle 1 proposal call&lt;/a&gt; was released today. The &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html"&gt;TESS Guest Investigator (GI) Program&lt;/a&gt; solicits proposals for the acquisition and analysis of scientific data from the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) mission, a NASA Explorer mission currently scheduled for …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE: the proposal deadline has been changed to October 6, 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://nspires.nasaprs.com/external/solicitations/summary.do?method=init&amp;amp;solId={7136D288-E4F8-8657-F280-6A4318467883}&amp;amp;path=open"&gt;Cycle 1 proposal call&lt;/a&gt; was released today. The &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html"&gt;TESS Guest Investigator (GI) Program&lt;/a&gt; solicits proposals for the acquisition and analysis of scientific data from the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) mission, a NASA Explorer mission currently scheduled for launch no later than June 2018. In a 2-year, near all-sky survey, TESS will monitor the brightness of nearby, bright F, G, K, and M stars in order to photometrically search for transiting planets smaller than Neptune. TESS will monitor the brightness of more than 200,000 stars spread over the celestial sphere with a photometric sensitivity sufficient to permit detection of transiting planets with radii less than 2.5 Earth radii. The mission’s high-precision, continuous baseline photometric capability is also well suited for variability and asteroseismology research and analyses of both Galactic and extragalactic astrophysical sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Observations associated with the TESS Guest Investigator (GI) Cycle 1 solicitation will begin immediately following the successful ~60-day scientific commissioning of the spacecraft. Proposals submitted to this program should be for new science investigations of the southern ecliptic hemisphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phase-1 proposals are due by 4:30 pm Eastern time on September 29, 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS Science Support Center at KepSciCon</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-science-support-center-at-kepscicon.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-16T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-06-16T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-06-16:/docs/tess/tess-science-support-center-at-kepscicon.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We will be hosting a breakout session at the Kepler Science Conference, at NASA Ames, CA.
The session will be at 1.30pm on Wednesday Jun 21 and will focus on allowing the community to talk directly to the TESS Science Support Center team, and additionally talk to the folks …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We will be hosting a breakout session at the Kepler Science Conference, at NASA Ames, CA.
The session will be at 1.30pm on Wednesday Jun 21 and will focus on allowing the community to talk directly to the TESS Science Support Center team, and additionally talk to the folks from the ExoFOP team. So please come along, and engage. We might also have some coloring books and stickers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS team at AAS 230</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-team-at-aas-230.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-15T10:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-05-15T10:01:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-05-15:/docs/tess/tess-team-at-aas-230.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://aas.org/meetings/aas230"&gt;230th American Astronomical Society&lt;/a&gt; is just around the corner. Team members from TESS's Science Support Center will be there to represent the mission. Come find us at at our booth where we will be joined by NExScI, Kepler/K2 and the Exoplanet Program Office. We will be available to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://aas.org/meetings/aas230"&gt;230th American Astronomical Society&lt;/a&gt; is just around the corner. Team members from TESS's Science Support Center will be there to represent the mission. Come find us at at our booth where we will be joined by NExScI, Kepler/K2 and the Exoplanet Program Office. We will be available to answer your questions and help you understand the feasibility of planned observations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>TESS Observatory Guide now available</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-observatory-guide-now-available.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-28T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-28T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Josh Schlieder</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-04-28:/docs/tess/tess-observatory-guide-now-available.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;To aid in the development in potential TESS science investigations we have created a &lt;a href="docs/TESS_observatory_guide_v1.1.pdf"&gt;TESS Observatory Guide&lt;/a&gt;. This document serves two purposes. The first is to provide a comprehensive description of the TESS  observatory design, operations, and capabilities. The second is to provide potential proposers detailed information relevant to preparing …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;To aid in the development in potential TESS science investigations we have created a &lt;a href="docs/TESS_observatory_guide_v1.1.pdf"&gt;TESS Observatory Guide&lt;/a&gt;. This document serves two purposes. The first is to provide a comprehensive description of the TESS  observatory design, operations, and capabilities. The second is to provide potential proposers detailed information relevant to preparing proposals for the  TESS GI program. This includes descriptions of  TESS data processing and data products and GI program procedures, services, and tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a living document. Comments are greatly appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Volunteer to review proposals</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/volunteer-to-review-proposals.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-28T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-28T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-04-28:/docs/tess/volunteer-to-review-proposals.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Science Support Center is responsible for organizing the review of proposals submitted to the TESS Guest Investigator program. Our first cycle deadline will be on September 29, 2017, with the in-person peer review likely taking place in mid-December. We are currently looking for volunteers with expertise in astrophysics …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Science Support Center is responsible for organizing the review of proposals submitted to the TESS Guest Investigator program. Our first cycle deadline will be on September 29, 2017, with the in-person peer review likely taking place in mid-December. We are currently looking for volunteers with expertise in astrophysics and exoplanet science to serve on our review panel. The requirements are that you have a PhD or relevant experience (so this opportunity isn't open to graduate students), and that you are not intending to PI a TESS Cycle 1 proposal (it's fine if you later choose to submit a proposal, but we would then not invite you to the review). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please get in touch by sending your name, institution, and areas of expertise to &lt;a href="mailto:tessgi@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov"&gt;tessgi@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov&lt;/a&gt;, or filling in &lt;a href="https://goo.gl/forms/p4ZqiTQSEHjbM6nz2"&gt;this form&lt;/a&gt;. As a guide, we are anticipating having panels made up of an approximately 50/50 split between postdocs and more senior scientists. Topics we are particularly interested in recruiting reviewers for are exoplanet science, asteroseismology, stellar activity, binary stars, and supernova observations. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Tell us about the software tool and data products you would like</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tell-us-about-the-software-tool-and-data-products-you-would-like.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-21T14:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-21T14:01:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-04-21:/docs/tess/tell-us-about-the-software-tool-and-data-products-you-would-like.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Science Support Center at NASA Goddard is currently collecting input from the scientific community on what tools and data products you would like to see developed. We have some plans but we are seeking more input. What do you need to achieve your science goals? Get in touch …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Science Support Center at NASA Goddard is currently collecting input from the scientific community on what tools and data products you would like to see developed. We have some plans but we are seeking more input. What do you need to achieve your science goals? Get in touch at &lt;a href="mailto:tessgi@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov"&gt;tessgi@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Space hardware development and going well</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/space-hardware-development-and-going-well.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-17T10:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-17T10:01:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-04-17:/docs/tess/space-hardware-development-and-going-well.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS hardware development is progressing well. All four cameras are currently being tested and are performing as expected. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TESS is a NASA Explorer class mission.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Development of new TESS website</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/development-of-new-tess-website.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-17T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-17T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-04-17:/docs/tess/development-of-new-tess-website.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) Science Support Center team is transitioning to a new website. This is that website. Lots of content on the Guest Investigator program is coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category></entry></feed>