<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>TESS</title><link href="https://tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov/</id><updated>2017-04-28T10:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Volunteer to review proposals</title><link href="https://tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov/volunteer-to-review-proposals.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-28T10:00:00-04:00</published><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-04-28:volunteer-to-review-proposals.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Community Science Center is responsible for organizing the review of proposals submitted to the TESS Guest Investigator program. Our first cycle deadline is anticipated to be in early approximately October, with the in-person peer review likely taking place in early December. We are currently looking for volunteers with expertise in astrophysics and exoplanet science to serve on our review panel. The requirements are that you have a PhD or relevant experience (so this opportunity isn't open to Grad Students), and that you are not intending to PI a TESS Cycle 1 proposal (it's fine you later choose to submit a proposal, but we would then not invite you to the review). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please get in touch by sending you name, institution to areas of expertise &lt;a href="mailto:tessgi@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov"&gt;tessgi@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov&lt;/a&gt;, or filling in &lt;a href="https://goo.gl/forms/p4ZqiTQSEHjbM6nz2"&gt;this form&lt;/a&gt;. As a guide, we are anticipating on having panels made up of an approximately 50/50 split between postdocs and more senior scientist. Topics we are particularly interesting in recruiting reviewers for are exoplanet science, asteroseismology, stellar activity, binary stars, and supernova observations. &lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Tell us about the software tool and data products you would like</title><link href="https://tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov/tell-us-about-the-software-tool-and-data-products-you-would-like.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-21T14:01:00-04:00</published><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-04-21:tell-us-about-the-software-tool-and-data-products-you-would-like.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Community Science Cneter at NASA Goddard are currently collecting input from the scientific community on what you would like to see developed. We have some plans but we are seeking more input. What do you need to achieve your science goals? Get in touch at &lt;a href="mailto:tessgi@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov"&gt;tessgi@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Space hardware development and going well</title><link href="https://tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov/space-hardware-development-and-going-well.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-17T10:01:00-04:00</published><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-04-17:space-hardware-development-and-going-well.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS hardware development is progressing well. All four camera are currently being tested and performing excellently. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TESS is a NASA Explorer class mission.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Development of new TESS website</title><link href="https://tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov/development-of-new-tess-website.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-17T10:00:00-04:00</published><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-04-17:development-of-new-tess-website.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite are transitioning to a news website. This is that website. Lots more content coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>