<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>TESS</title><link href="https://tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov/</id><updated>2017-06-29T10:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>TESS Guest Investigator Cycle 1 released</title><link href="https://tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov/tess-guest-investigator-cycle-1-released.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-29T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-06-29T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-06-29:/tess-guest-investigator-cycle-1-released.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://nspires.nasaprs.com/external/solicitations/summary.do?method=init&amp;amp;solId={7136D288-E4F8-8657-F280-6A4318467883}&amp;amp;path=open"&gt;Cycle 1 proposal call&lt;/a&gt; was released today. The &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html"&gt;TESS Guest Investigator (GI) Program&lt;/a&gt; solicits proposals for the acquisition and analysis of scientific data from the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) mission, a NASA Explorer mission currently scheduled for launch no later than June 2018. In a 2-year, near all-sky …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://nspires.nasaprs.com/external/solicitations/summary.do?method=init&amp;amp;solId={7136D288-E4F8-8657-F280-6A4318467883}&amp;amp;path=open"&gt;Cycle 1 proposal call&lt;/a&gt; was released today. The &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html"&gt;TESS Guest Investigator (GI) Program&lt;/a&gt; solicits proposals for the acquisition and analysis of scientific data from the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) mission, a NASA Explorer mission currently scheduled for launch no later than June 2018. In a 2-year, near all-sky survey, TESS will monitor the brightness of nearby, bright F, G, K, and M stars in order to photometrically search for transiting planets smaller than Neptune. TESS will monitor the brightness of more than 200,000 stars spread over the celestial sphere with a photometric sensitivity sufficient to permit detection of transiting planets with a radius less than 2.5 Earth radii. The mission’s high-precision, continuous baseline photometric capability is also well suited for variability and asteroseismology research and analyses of both Galactic and extragalactic astrophysical sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Observations associated with the TESS Guest Investigator (GI) Cycle 1 solicitation will begin immediately following the successful ~60-day scientific commissioning of the spacecraft. Proposals submitted to this program should be for new science investigations of the southern ecliptic hemisphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phase-1 proposals are due by 4:30 pm Eastern time on September 29, 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>TESS Science Support Center at KepSciCon</title><link href="https://tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov/tess-science-support-center-at-kepscicon.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-16T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-06-16T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-06-16:/tess-science-support-center-at-kepscicon.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We will be hosting a breakout session at the Kepler Science Conference, at NASA Ames, CA.
The session will be at 1.30pm on Wednesday Jun 21 and will focus on allowing the community to talk directly to the TESS Science Support Center team, and additionally talk to the folks …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We will be hosting a breakout session at the Kepler Science Conference, at NASA Ames, CA.
The session will be at 1.30pm on Wednesday Jun 21 and will focus on allowing the community to talk directly to the TESS Science Support Center team, and additionally talk to the folks from the ExoFOP team. So please come along, and engage. We might also have some coloring books and stickers.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>TESS team at AAS 230</title><link href="https://tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov/tess-team-at-aas-230.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-15T10:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-05-15T10:01:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-05-15:/tess-team-at-aas-230.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://aas.org/meetings/aas230"&gt;230th American Astronomical Society&lt;/a&gt; is just around the corner. Team members from TESS's Science Support Center will be there to represent the mission. Come find us at at our booth where we will be joined by NExScI, Kepler/K2 and the Exoplanet Program Office. We will be available to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://aas.org/meetings/aas230"&gt;230th American Astronomical Society&lt;/a&gt; is just around the corner. Team members from TESS's Science Support Center will be there to represent the mission. Come find us at at our booth where we will be joined by NExScI, Kepler/K2 and the Exoplanet Program Office. We will be available to answer your questions and help you understand the feasibility of planned observations.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>TESS Observatory Guide now available</title><link href="https://tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov/tess-observatory-guide-now-available.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-28T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-28T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Josh Schlieder</name></author><id>tag:tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-04-28:/tess-observatory-guide-now-available.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;To aid in the development in potential TESS science investigations we have created a [TESS Observatory Guide][docs/TESS_observatory_guide_v1.0.pdf]. This document serves two purposes. The first is to provide a comprehensive description of the TESS  observatory design, operations, and capabilities. The second is to provide potential proposers detailed …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;To aid in the development in potential TESS science investigations we have created a [TESS Observatory Guide][docs/TESS_observatory_guide_v1.0.pdf]. This document serves two purposes. The first is to provide a comprehensive description of the TESS  observatory design, operations, and capabilities. The second is to provide potential proposers detailed information relevant to preparing proposals for the  TESS GI program. This includes descriptions of  TESS data processing and data products and GI program procedures, services, and tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a living document. Comments are greatly appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Volunteer to review proposals</title><link href="https://tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov/volunteer-to-review-proposals.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-28T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-28T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-04-28:/volunteer-to-review-proposals.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Science Support Center is responsible for organizing the review of proposals submitted to the TESS Guest Investigator program. Our first cycle deadline is anticipated to be in early approximately October, with the in-person peer review likely taking place in early December. We are currently looking for volunteers with …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Science Support Center is responsible for organizing the review of proposals submitted to the TESS Guest Investigator program. Our first cycle deadline is anticipated to be in early approximately October, with the in-person peer review likely taking place in early December. We are currently looking for volunteers with expertise in astrophysics and exoplanet science to serve on our review panel. The requirements are that you have a PhD or relevant experience (so this opportunity isn't open to Grad Students), and that you are not intending to PI a TESS Cycle 1 proposal (it's fine you later choose to submit a proposal, but we would then not invite you to the review). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please get in touch by sending you name, institution to areas of expertise &lt;a href="mailto:tessgi@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov"&gt;tessgi@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov&lt;/a&gt;, or filling in &lt;a href="https://goo.gl/forms/p4ZqiTQSEHjbM6nz2"&gt;this form&lt;/a&gt;. As a guide, we are anticipating on having panels made up of an approximately 50/50 split between postdocs and more senior scientist. Topics we are particularly interesting in recruiting reviewers for are exoplanet science, asteroseismology, stellar activity, binary stars, and supernova observations. &lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Tell us about the software tool and data products you would like</title><link href="https://tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov/tell-us-about-the-software-tool-and-data-products-you-would-like.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-21T14:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-21T14:01:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-04-21:/tell-us-about-the-software-tool-and-data-products-you-would-like.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Science Support Center at NASA Goddard are currently collecting input from the scientific community on what you would like to see developed. We have some plans but we are seeking more input. What do you need to achieve your science goals? Get in touch at &lt;a href="mailto:tessgi@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov"&gt;tessgi@bigbang.gsfc …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Science Support Center at NASA Goddard are currently collecting input from the scientific community on what you would like to see developed. We have some plans but we are seeking more input. What do you need to achieve your science goals? Get in touch at &lt;a href="mailto:tessgi@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov"&gt;tessgi@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Space hardware development and going well</title><link href="https://tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov/space-hardware-development-and-going-well.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-17T10:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-17T10:01:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-04-17:/space-hardware-development-and-going-well.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS hardware development is progressing well. All four camera are currently being tested and performing excellently. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TESS is a NASA Explorer class mission.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS hardware development is progressing well. All four camera are currently being tested and performing excellently. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TESS is a NASA Explorer class mission.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Development of new TESS website</title><link href="https://tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov/development-of-new-tess-website.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-17T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-17T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:tessgi.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-04-17:/development-of-new-tess-website.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite are transitioning to a new website. This is that website. Lots more content coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite are transitioning to a new website. This is that website. Lots more content coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>