<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>TESS</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/</id><updated>2018-02-15T02:01:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>TESS arrives at Kennedy Space Center, and updated launch date</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-arrives-at-kennedy-space-center-and-updated-launch-date.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-15T02:01:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-15T02:01:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-02-15:/docs/tess/tess-arrives-at-kennedy-space-center-and-updated-launch-date.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS has been transported from Orbital ATK in Dulles, VA, to Kennedy Space Center where it will be &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/feature/goddard/2018/nasa-s-transiting-exoplanet-survey-satellite-arrives-at-kennedy-space-center-for-launch"&gt;prepped for launch&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been an update to the launch date. According to NASA, the launch will be no earlier than April 16, pending range approval.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:67%;" src="images/tess-at-ksc.jpg"&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS has been transported from Orbital ATK in Dulles, VA, to Kennedy Space Center where it will be &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/feature/goddard/2018/nasa-s-transiting-exoplanet-survey-satellite-arrives-at-kennedy-space-center-for-launch"&gt;prepped for launch&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been an update to the launch date. According to NASA, the launch will be no earlier than April 16, pending range approval.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:67%;" src="images/tess-at-ksc.jpg"&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>TESS Highlights at AAS 231</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-highlights-at-aas-231.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-29T02:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-29T02:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Elisa Quintana</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-01-29:/docs/tess/tess-highlights-at-aas-231.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS team members and scientists participated in a number of successful events at the &lt;a href="https://aas.org/meetings/aas231"&gt;231st American Astronomical Society&lt;/a&gt; meeting in National Harbor, MD, in January 2018. &lt;a href="tess-team-at-aas-231.html"&gt;TESS activities&lt;/a&gt; included a joint evening splinter session on NASA's TESS and K2 missions, a special seminar for science writers, and a number of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESS team members and scientists participated in a number of successful events at the &lt;a href="https://aas.org/meetings/aas231"&gt;231st American Astronomical Society&lt;/a&gt; meeting in National Harbor, MD, in January 2018. &lt;a href="tess-team-at-aas-231.html"&gt;TESS activities&lt;/a&gt; included a joint evening splinter session on NASA's TESS and K2 missions, a special seminar for science writers, and a number of talks, posters, and hyperwall presentations. Team members from MIT and NASA Goddard were also on hand to answer questions about the mission and feasibility of planned observations at a TESS booth in the exhibition hall, and there was much excitement for the upcoming launch throughout the meeting. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A special &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/sites/default/files/atoms/files/tesssciencewritersguidefinal.pdf"&gt;TESS Science Writers Guide&lt;/a&gt; was out together &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:67%;" src="images/science-writers-guide.png"&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
TESS Science Writer's Guide available in PDF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:67%;" src="images/diana-hyperwall.jpg"&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
NASA Hyperwall Stories: Finding New Worlds with the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite, Diana Dragomir (MIT)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:67%;" src="images/michael-hyperwall.jpg"&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
NASA Hyperwall Stories: TESS Mission Overview, Michael Fasnaugh (MIT)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:67%;" src="images/stephen-hyperwall.jpg"&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
NASA Hyperwall Stories: TESS Guest Investigator Program, Stephen Rinehart (NASA GSFC)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:67%;" src="images/aas231 - booth.jpg"&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
TESS team members staffing the TESS Booth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:67%;" src="images/aas231 - booth2.jpg"&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
TESS team members staffing the TESS Booth.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Guest Investigator Program Cycle 1 results available</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/guest-investigator-program-cycle-1-results-available.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-25T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-25T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-01-25:/docs/tess/guest-investigator-program-cycle-1-results-available.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The selection of TESS Guest Investigator Program Cycle 1 proposals has been finalized. A &lt;a href="approved-programs.html"&gt;full list of selected programs&lt;/a&gt; is available. TESS is scheduled to launch by the end of March. If this schedule holds, science operation will begin at the start of June, with the first data reaching &lt;a href="http://archive.stsci.edu/tess"&gt;the …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The selection of TESS Guest Investigator Program Cycle 1 proposals has been finalized. A &lt;a href="approved-programs.html"&gt;full list of selected programs&lt;/a&gt; is available. TESS is scheduled to launch by the end of March. If this schedule holds, science operation will begin at the start of June, with the first data reaching &lt;a href="http://archive.stsci.edu/tess"&gt;the archive&lt;/a&gt; at the beginning of December. Grants will be released when data is publicly available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The over-subscription factor for this program was extremely high (4.5). Many highly rated programs were not able to be selected for funding. However, we have good news. All full-frame-image data will be released publicly with no exclusive use period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, we anticipate that the number of executed 2-minute cadence target programs will significantly exceed the number that we were able to fund. Therefore, even though a particular program may not have been selected for funding there is still a good chance that it will be either partially for full executed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We anticipate that target lists for the first sector to be available within a few weeks of launch. When available, we will make that information available.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>TESS Input Catalog Version 6 (TIC-6) is now online at MAST</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-input-catalog-version-6-tic-6-is-now-online-at-mast.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-23T13:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-23T13:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Elisa Quintana</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-01-23:/docs/tess/tess-input-catalog-version-6-tic-6-is-now-online-at-mast.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Input Catalot Version 6 (TIC-6) is now available at MAST.  This includes access via the &lt;a href="https://mast.stsci.edu/portal/Mashup/Clients/Mast/Portal.html"&gt;MAST portal&lt;/a&gt;, using &lt;a href="http://mastweb.stsci.edu/mcasjobs/"&gt;CasJobs&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://archive.stsci.edu/missions/tess/index.html"&gt;bulk downloads&lt;/a&gt;.  The &lt;a href="https://archive.stsci.edu/tess/"&gt;MAST TESS page&lt;/a&gt; has all the information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The live &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1zdiKMs4Ld4cXZ2DW4lMX-fuxAF6hPHTjqjIwGqnfjqI/edit"&gt;TIC-6 Data Release Notes&lt;/a&gt; provide information on the changes from TIC Version 5 (TIC-5). Documentation on …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Input Catalot Version 6 (TIC-6) is now available at MAST.  This includes access via the &lt;a href="https://mast.stsci.edu/portal/Mashup/Clients/Mast/Portal.html"&gt;MAST portal&lt;/a&gt;, using &lt;a href="http://mastweb.stsci.edu/mcasjobs/"&gt;CasJobs&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://archive.stsci.edu/missions/tess/index.html"&gt;bulk downloads&lt;/a&gt;.  The &lt;a href="https://archive.stsci.edu/tess/"&gt;MAST TESS page&lt;/a&gt; has all the information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The live &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1zdiKMs4Ld4cXZ2DW4lMX-fuxAF6hPHTjqjIwGqnfjqI/edit"&gt;TIC-6 Data Release Notes&lt;/a&gt; provide information on the changes from TIC Version 5 (TIC-5). Documentation on the content of the TIC can be found &lt;a href="https://archive.stsci.edu/missions/tess/doc/tic_v5_drn.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Note this documentation is specific to TIC Version 5 (TIC-5), so please refer to the release notes for the most up-to-date documentation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questions can be sent to our &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/helpdesk.html"&gt;help desk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the TESS Target Selection Working Group and TESS team members for their hard work in making this resource available! Also thanks to Scott Fleming and the team at MAST for supporting the archiving and documentation of the TIC catalogs.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>TESS team at AAS 231</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-team-at-aas-231.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-04T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-04T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2018-01-04:/docs/tess/tess-team-at-aas-231.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS team will are putting on a number of events at this year's &lt;a href="https://aas.org/meetings/aas231"&gt;American Astronomical Society&lt;/a&gt; in National Harbor, MD. In addition to those events the team are putting on, there are numerous talks from scientist excited to get their hands on the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="evening-splinter-session"&gt;Evening splinter session&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NASA's TESS …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS team will are putting on a number of events at this year's &lt;a href="https://aas.org/meetings/aas231"&gt;American Astronomical Society&lt;/a&gt; in National Harbor, MD. In addition to those events the team are putting on, there are numerous talks from scientist excited to get their hands on the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="evening-splinter-session"&gt;Evening splinter session&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NASA's TESS and K2 missions will be hosting an evening splinter session on Tuesday (Jan 9) at 7.30pm in National Harbor Room 7 of the Gaylord Resort and Convention Center. The event will have limited quantities of snacks and drinks available. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img class="img-responsive" style="max-width:67%;" src="images/AAS NationHarbor-Jan2018_poster-Spl-K2_TESS.png"&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="hyperwall-talks-at-the-nasa-booth"&gt;Hyperwall Talks at the NASA booth&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="tuesday-january-09-2018"&gt;Tuesday, January 09, 2018&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5:15-5:30 PM, Finding New Worlds with the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite, Diana Dragomir (MIT)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id="wednesday-january-10-2018"&gt;Wednesday, January 10, 2018&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9:35-9:50 AM, TESS Mission Overview, Michael Fasnaugh (MIT)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id="thursday-january-11-2018"&gt;Thursday, January 11, 2018&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9:45-10:00 AM, TESS Guest Investigator Program, Stephen Rinehart (NASA GSFC)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="an-incomplete-list-of-tess-related-talks-and-posters"&gt;An incomplete list of TESS related talks and posters&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="tuesday-january-09-2018_1"&gt;Tuesday, January 09, 2018&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5 id="200-pm-330-pm-national-harbor-11-gaylord-at-national-harbor-128-extrasolar-planets-ii"&gt;2:00 PM-3:30 PM, National Harbor 11 (Gaylord at National Harbor), 128. Extrasolar Planets II&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3:00-3:10 PM 128.06. Simulated JWST/NIRISS Transit Spectroscopy of Anticipated TESS Planets Compared to Select Discoveries from Space-Based and Ground-Based Surveys D. Louie; D. Deming; L. Albert; L. Bouma; J. Bean; M. Lopez-Morales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5 id="530-pm-630-pm-prince-georges-exhibit-hall-gaylord-at-national-harbor-150-computation-data-handling-image-analysis-poster-session"&gt;5:30 PM-6:30 PM, Prince Georges Exhibit Hall (Gaylord at National Harbor), 150 . Computation, Data Handling, Image Analysis Poster Session&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;150.39. Exploring Algorithms for Stellar Light Curves With TESS D. Buzasi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id="wednesday-january-10-2018_1"&gt;Wednesday, January 10, 2018&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5 id="530-pm-630-pm-prince-georges-exhibit-hall-gaylord-at-national-harbor-246-extrasolar-planets-detection-poster-session"&gt;5:30 PM-6:30 PM, Prince Georges Exhibit Hall (Gaylord at National Harbor), 246. Extrasolar Planets: Detection Poster Session&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;246.05. Transit Precovery: Determining Ephemerides for Long-Period TESS Detections with KELT Photometry X. Yao; J. Pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;246.23. Prospects for Ground-Based Detection and Follow-up of TESS-Discovered Exoplanets M. Varakian; D. Deming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;246.31. High-Resolution Spectroscopy at the Wyoming Infrared Observatory: Setting TESS Science on FHiRE H. Jang-Condell; M.J. Pierce; C.A. Pilachowski; H. Kobulnicky; J.N. McLane&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id="thursday-january-11-2018_1"&gt;Thursday, January 11, 2018&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5 id="1000-am-1130-am-maryland-ballroom-a-gaylord-at-national-harbor-303-detection-of-extrasolar-planets-iii"&gt;10:00 AM-11:30 AM, Maryland Ballroom A (Gaylord at National Harbor), 303. Detection of Extrasolar Planets III&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:00-10:10 AM 303.01. Preparing for TESS: Precision Ground-based Light-curves of Newly Discovered Transiting Exoplanets Y. Li; G. Stefansson; S. Mahadevan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5 id="1000-am-1130-am-national-harbor-11-gaylord-at-national-harbor-310-extrasolar-planets-v"&gt;10:00 AM-11:30 AM, National Harbor 11 (Gaylord at National Harbor), 310. Extrasolar Planets V&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:00-10:20 AM 310.02D. Precision Stellar and Planetary Astrophysics with TESS and Gaia D.J. Stevens&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:20-10:30 AM 310.03. Stellar activity for every TESS star in the Southern sky W.S. Howard; N. Law; O. Fors; H.T. Corbett; J. Ratzloff; D. del Ser&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5 id="200-pm-330-pm-national-harbor-7-gaylord-at-national-harbor-ground-based-support-for-nasa-exoplanet-mission-splinter-meeting"&gt;2:00 PM-3:30 PM, National Harbor 7 (Gaylord at National Harbor), Ground Based Support for NASA Exoplanet Mission, Splinter Meeting&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h4 id="friday-january-12-2018"&gt;Friday, January 12, 2018&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5 id="1000-am-1130-am-maryland-ballroom-a-gaylord-at-national-harbor-403-detection-of-extrasolar-planets-iv"&gt;10:00 AM-11:30 AM, Maryland Ballroom A (Gaylord at National Harbor), 403. Detection of Extrasolar Planets IV&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:40-10:50 AM 403.04. The TESS Input Catalog and Selection of Targets for the TESS Transit Search J. Pepper; K.G. Stassun; M. Paegert; R. Oelkers; N.M. De Lee; G. Torres&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:50-11:00 AM 403.05. Maximizing the TESS Mission’s Yield of Long-Period Planets
D. Dragomir; B.S. Gaudi; S. Villanueva; I. Crossfield; X. Huang; I. Ribas; S. Quinn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11:20-11:30 AM 403.08. Simulating the Exoplanet Yield from the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite T. Barclay; J. Pepper; J. Schlieder; E. Quintana&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5 id="100-pm-200-pm-prince-georges-exhibit-hall-gaylord-at-national-harbor-439-extrasolar-planets-late-poster-session"&gt;1:00 PM-2:00 PM, Prince Georges Exhibit Hall (Gaylord at National Harbor), 439. Extrasolar Planets (Late) Poster Session&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;439.07. A PSF photometry tool for NASA's Kepler, K2, and TESS missions J. De Miranda Cardoso; G. Barentsen; C.L. Hedges; M.A. Gully-Santiago; A. Cody; B. Montet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;439.08. TESS Follow-up Observing Program (TFOP) Working Group:A Mission-led Effort to Coordinate Community Resources to Confirm TESS Planets K. Collins; S.N. Quinn; D.W. Latham; J. Christiansen; D. Ciardi; D. Dragomir; I. Crossfield; S. Seager&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;439.09. TESS Data Processing and Quick-look Pipeline M. Fausnaugh; X. Huang; A. Glidden; N. Guerrero&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;439.10. PyKE3: data analysis tools for NASA's Kepler, K2, and TESS missions C.L. Hedges; J. De Miranda Cardoso; G. Barentsen; M.A. Gully-Santiago; A. Cody; T. Barclay; M. Still&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;439.11. TESS Objects of Interest N. Guerrero; A. Glidden; M. Fausnaugh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;439.12. TESS Ground System Operations and Data Products A. Glidden; N. Guerrero; M. Fausnaugh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Proposal submission now closed</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/proposal-submission-now-closed.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-10-09T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-10-09T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-10-09:/docs/tess/proposal-submission-now-closed.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the many people who submitted Cycle 1 TESS GI proposals, we are very pleased with the response. We are now in the proposal of organizing the review of proposals. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We received over 140 proposals for nearly 100,000 unique 2-min cadence targets. About 60% of proposal were stellar …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the many people who submitted Cycle 1 TESS GI proposals, we are very pleased with the response. We are now in the proposal of organizing the review of proposals. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We received over 140 proposals for nearly 100,000 unique 2-min cadence targets. About 60% of proposal were stellar astrophysics investigations (primarily studies of activity and asteroseismology), a third were focused on exoplanets, and the remaining included extragalactic and solar system investigations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We anticipate that we will be oversubscribed by a factor of six in large programs, a factor of four in small programs, and a factor of five for 2-min cadence targets.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Release of TESS cool dwarf catalog</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/release-of-tess-cool-dwarf-catalog.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-10-03T09:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-10-03T09:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-10-03:/docs/tess/release-of-tess-cool-dwarf-catalog.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A paper describing efforts to create a catalog of cool dwarf stars for TESS target selection is available on &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1710.00193"&gt;the arXiv&lt;/a&gt;. This release details the stellar properties of dwarf stars cooler than 4000K, with the specific aim to help identify exoplanet search targets to be observed by TESS at 2-min …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A paper describing efforts to create a catalog of cool dwarf stars for TESS target selection is available on &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1710.00193"&gt;the arXiv&lt;/a&gt;. This release details the stellar properties of dwarf stars cooler than 4000K, with the specific aim to help identify exoplanet search targets to be observed by TESS at 2-min cadence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TESS has the opportunity to search tens of thousands of nearby, cool, late K and M-type dwarfs for transiting exoplanets, an order of magnitude more than current or previous transiting exoplanet surveys. This  catalog is incorporated into the &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html#tess-input-catalog-tic"&gt;TESS Input Catalog&lt;/a&gt; and TESS Candidate Target List(proposing-investigations.html#candidate-target-list-ctl).&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Target list pointers</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/target-list-pointers.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-26T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-26T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-09-26:/docs/tess/target-list-pointers.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The proposal deadline is just over a week away and many of you are deep into the proposal writing process. Here are two small reminders/requests for target lists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TESS Guest Investigator Cycle 1 is awarding targets in the Southern Ecliptic Hemisphere. Northern Ecliptic targets will be solicited in Cycle …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The proposal deadline is just over a week away and many of you are deep into the proposal writing process. Here are two small reminders/requests for target lists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TESS Guest Investigator Cycle 1 is awarding targets in the Southern Ecliptic Hemisphere. Northern Ecliptic targets will be solicited in Cycle 2. Including targets that can't be observed won't technically impact your proposal - we will just remove them - but it may suggest to reviewers that you haven't done your homework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your target lists should be in priority order. We many choose to award less than the full proposed target list; providing your targets in ranked order enables us to do this. For proposals with very large target lists, we recommend mentioning in the proposal the minimum number of target required to accomplish the scientific goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Cycle 1 proposal deadline change</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/cycle-1-proposal-deadline-change.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-19T15:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-19T15:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-09-19:/docs/tess/cycle-1-proposal-deadline-change.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The deadline for Cycle 1 proposals has been changed to October 6, 2017 at 4:30 pm Eastern time&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give more time to proposers who are without power because of Hurricane Irma, the Phase-1 proposal due date for Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) Guest Investigator Program - Cycle 1 has …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The deadline for Cycle 1 proposals has been changed to October 6, 2017 at 4:30 pm Eastern time&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give more time to proposers who are without power because of Hurricane Irma, the Phase-1 proposal due date for Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) Guest Investigator Program - Cycle 1 has been delayed one week to October 6, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Amendment to the NASA Research Announcement "Research Opportunities in Space and Earth Sciences (ROSES) 2017" (NNH17ZDA001N) has be posted on the &lt;a href="http://nspires.nasaprs.com"&gt;NASA research opportunity homepage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technical questions concerning this program element may be directed to &lt;a href="mailto:patricia.t.boyd@nasa.gov"&gt;Patricia Boyd&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The NASA point of contact for programmatic information is &lt;a href="mailto:martin.still@nasa.gov"&gt;Martin Still&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Release of Web TESS Target Tool</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/release-of-web-tess-target-tool.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-14T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-14T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-09-14:/docs/tess/release-of-web-tess-target-tool.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are delighted to announce the release of the &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/cgi-bin/tess/webtess/wtm.py"&gt;Web TESS Target Tool&lt;/a&gt;. The tool enables potential TESS users to:
&lt;em&gt; determine whether their targets are observable in TESS Cycle 1
&lt;/em&gt; estimate the noise level on their targets
* calculate a brightness of their targets in the TESS bandpass&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The functionality of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are delighted to announce the release of the &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/cgi-bin/tess/webtess/wtm.py"&gt;Web TESS Target Tool&lt;/a&gt;. The tool enables potential TESS users to:
&lt;em&gt; determine whether their targets are observable in TESS Cycle 1
&lt;/em&gt; estimate the noise level on their targets
* calculate a brightness of their targets in the TESS bandpass&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The functionality of this tool is also available via command line tools &lt;a href="proposal-tools.html#ticgen"&gt;ticgen&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="proposal-tools.html#tvguide"&gt;tvguide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For comments and questions about this and any other aspects of the Cycle 1 call for proposals, contact us at &lt;a href="mailto:tessgi@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov"&gt;tessgi@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Release of a software tool to calculate TESS magnitudes and noise level</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/release-of-a-software-tool-to-calculate-tess-magnitudes-and-noise-level.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-10T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-10T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-09-10:/docs/tess/release-of-a-software-tool-to-calculate-tess-magnitudes-and-noise-level.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are pleased to announce the release of a software tool known as &lt;a href="proposal-tools.html#ticgen"&gt;ticgen&lt;/a&gt; that an be used to calculate TESS magnitudes from various different bandpasses, and also calculates the TESS noise level for different brightness sources. The software is a command line tool and can be downloaded from our …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are pleased to announce the release of a software tool known as &lt;a href="proposal-tools.html#ticgen"&gt;ticgen&lt;/a&gt; that an be used to calculate TESS magnitudes from various different bandpasses, and also calculates the TESS noise level for different brightness sources. The software is a command line tool and can be downloaded from our &lt;a href="https://github.com/tessgi/ticgen"&gt;Github site&lt;/a&gt;, where we also provide more information. Both ticgen and our other software &lt;a href="proposal-tools.html#tvguide"&gt;tvguide&lt;/a&gt; can be used to aid users in writing proposals. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, we will soon be released a Web tool that combines the functionality of ticgen and &lt;a href="https://github.com/tessgi/tvguide"&gt;tvguide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Increase in target allocation for GI Program</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/increase-in-target-allocation-for-gi-program.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-09T11:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-09T11:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-09-09:/docs/tess/increase-in-target-allocation-for-gi-program.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The allocation of targets assigned to the Guest Investigator Program in Cycle 1 has been increased from 10,000 to 20,000 targets. Targets will be approximately evenly split over each of the 13 sectors, leading to around 1,500 targets per sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary aim of this increase is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The allocation of targets assigned to the Guest Investigator Program in Cycle 1 has been increased from 10,000 to 20,000 targets. Targets will be approximately evenly split over each of the 13 sectors, leading to around 1,500 targets per sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary aim of this increase is to increase the flexibility that large programs have in their target selection. With this increase in mind, we encourage wide-ranging investigations to consider how they might utilize this increase in available resources.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>TESS to observe bright stars at 2-min cadence</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-to-observe-bright-stars-at-2-min-cadence.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-09T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-09T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-09-09:/docs/tess/tess-to-observe-bright-stars-at-2-min-cadence.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS team has been working together to plan how to merge lists of targets are that are to be observed at two-minute cadence. As a result of these discussions the mission is committing to observing at two-minute cadence all stars that fall into the TESS field of view that …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS team has been working together to plan how to merge lists of targets are that are to be observed at two-minute cadence. As a result of these discussions the mission is committing to observing at two-minute cadence all stars that fall into the TESS field of view that are (a) brighter than 6th magnitude in the TESS bandpass, and (b) but are not too bright that their saturation bleed cannot be captured fully with a pixel mask. For Cycle-1 this accounts for approximately 6,000 stars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have made a slight modification to the &lt;a href="data/core-science-targets-v2.csv"&gt;list of targets&lt;/a&gt; that should not be included in TESS Cycle 1 GI proposals to search for transiting exoplanets using two-minute cadence data. This list now includes these 6,000 bright stars. This change is unlikely to significantly impact any proposals because these the majority of these bright stars are large (M-giants, B-stars, etc.). This makes detecting transiting planets challenging, and the detectability is unlikely to be improved with two-minute cadence over the full-frame image data.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>TESS-HERMES catalog of spectroscopic stellar parameters is now available</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-hermes-catalog-of-spectroscopic-stellar-parameters-is-now-available.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-24T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-24T13:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Elisa Quintana</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-08-24:/docs/tess/tess-hermes-catalog-of-spectroscopic-stellar-parameters-is-now-available.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A catalog of spectroscopic stellar parameters for stars in the TESS southern continuous viewing zone (CVZ) is now available and may prove a useful resource for &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html"&gt;TESS GI proposal preparation&lt;/a&gt;. Data taken by the High Efficiency and Resolution Multi-Element Spectrograph (HERMES) at the Anglo-Australian Telescope, as part of the TESS-HERMES …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A catalog of spectroscopic stellar parameters for stars in the TESS southern continuous viewing zone (CVZ) is now available and may prove a useful resource for &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html"&gt;TESS GI proposal preparation&lt;/a&gt;. Data taken by the High Efficiency and Resolution Multi-Element Spectrograph (HERMES) at the Anglo-Australian Telescope, as part of the TESS-HERMES survey, provides temperature, surface gravity, and metalicity for about 16,000 dwarf and subgiant stars with magnitudes 10&amp;lt;V&amp;lt;13.1, along with Bayesian estimates of stellar properties (distance, extinction, mass, radius, and age) using theoretical isochrones. Stellar surface gravity and radius are made available for an additional set of roughly 8,500 red giants. The TESS-HERMES catalog has identified over a hundred cool dwarfs that were flagged as giant stars in the TESS Input Catalog (TIC).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.physics.usyd.edu.au/tess-hermes/"&gt;TESS-HERMES survey website&lt;/a&gt;  provides links to the catalog (.csv and .fits) and tables describing the content of the catalogs. An article describing the survey (Sharma et al. 2017) can be found &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1707.05753"&gt;on the arxiv&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We thank Sanjib Sharma, Dennis Stello, and the HERMES team for their hard work in making this resource available in time for GI Cycle 1.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Cycle 1 proposal template available</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/cycle-1-proposal-template-available.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-08T15:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-08T15:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-08-08:/docs/tess/cycle-1-proposal-template-available.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE: the proposal deadline has been changed to October 6, 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have made available a &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html#proposal-templates"&gt;Microsoft Word format proposal template&lt;/a&gt;. The aim of creating this is to aid in preparing the proposal document and avoiding compliance issue. There is no requirement to use this template.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a reminder, proposals …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE: the proposal deadline has been changed to October 6, 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have made available a &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html#proposal-templates"&gt;Microsoft Word format proposal template&lt;/a&gt;. The aim of creating this is to aid in preparing the proposal document and avoiding compliance issue. There is no requirement to use this template.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a reminder, proposals should include a Science/Technical/Management section that does not exceed 4-pages long. This page limit includes references and figures. The proposals are due on September 29, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Update: we have also made available &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html#proposal-templates"&gt;Latex and PDF version of the template&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>TESS Guest Investigator Cycle 1 proposal submission page open</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-guest-investigator-cycle-1-proposal-submission-page-open.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-08T14:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-08T14:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-08-08:/docs/tess/tess-guest-investigator-cycle-1-proposal-submission-page-open.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;You can now submit TESS Cycle 1 proposals via the HEASARC's &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/ark/rps/"&gt;Remote Proposal System&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few things to note are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven't used ARK/RPS before, get an account now (it's easy, but don't wait till the last minute)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure your co-I's countries and institutions are recognized by …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;You can now submit TESS Cycle 1 proposals via the HEASARC's &lt;a href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/ark/rps/"&gt;Remote Proposal System&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few things to note are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven't used ARK/RPS before, get an account now (it's easy, but don't wait till the last minute)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure your co-I's countries and institutions are recognized by ARK - if not, ask them to be added to our list now&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You must "verify" the form, and pass the checks, before you can submit your proposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can discard/modify submitted proposals up until the deadline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're asking for 2-min data, note that there are two different ways to provide your target list: Into the RPS target form itself, or as a separate CSV file upload - the latter will only become possible after you submit your RPS form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>TESS Passes Critical Review</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-passes-critical-review.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-07T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-07T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-08-07:/docs/tess/tess-passes-critical-review.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;NASA's Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) has moved one step closer to launch after &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/feature/goddard/2017/nasa-s-transiting-exoplanet-survey-satellite-passes-critical-review"&gt;successfully passing its Systems Integration Review (SIR)&lt;/a&gt;, an independent review from independent technical and scientific experts who have deemed the mission ready to begin installation of its scientific instrument onto the spacecraft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that TESS has …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;NASA's Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) has moved one step closer to launch after &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/feature/goddard/2017/nasa-s-transiting-exoplanet-survey-satellite-passes-critical-review"&gt;successfully passing its Systems Integration Review (SIR)&lt;/a&gt;, an independent review from independent technical and scientific experts who have deemed the mission ready to begin installation of its scientific instrument onto the spacecraft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that TESS has completed this critical review, the mission's cameras and science data processing computer are scheduled to begin installation onto the spacecraft at Orbital ATK in Dulles, Virginia, over the next several weeks. Once successfully integrated, the spacecraft will spend the rest of the year undergoing rigorous testing to ensure the mission can withstand the harsh environment of space. The spacecraft is scheduled to ship in February to NASA's Kennedy Space Center in Florida for launch aboard a SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the Kepler telescope, by design there is a range of focus and image quality across the TESS camera's field of view. Recent measurements revealed the TESS cameras to have slightly reduced focus and image quality near the outer edge of the image when placed in the cold temperatures of space, and better camera focus and image quality towards the center of the image. The difference between the designed and measured focus and image quality will not affect the mission's science goals.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Error in a small number of TIC v5 surface gravities</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/error-in-a-small-number-of-tic-v5-surface-gravities.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-01T14:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-01T14:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-08-01:/docs/tess/error-in-a-small-number-of-tic-v5-surface-gravities.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The surface gravities reported in column 67 of the TESS Input Catalog version 5 (TIC-5), do not accurately represent the expected surface gravities using the reported values for mass (column 73) and radii (column 71). This only affects stars where the stellar properties were calculated using available parallax information (the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The surface gravities reported in column 67 of the TESS Input Catalog version 5 (TIC-5), do not accurately represent the expected surface gravities using the reported values for mass (column 73) and radii (column 71). This only affects stars where the stellar properties were calculated using available parallax information (the stellar properties flag is set to "plx" in column 64 and no other quantities in the TIC are affected. TIC users can either calculate the surface gravity using the provided mass and radius values, or use a &lt;a href="http://archive.stsci.edu/missions/tess/catalogs/tic_v5/tic5_logg_fix.csv"&gt;provided data file&lt;/a&gt; to access the appropriately calculated values. This fix will be built in to the next version of the TIC, version 6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, for TIC v5, numerical columns with values of exactly 0 are actually null values. Starting in TIC v6, these will be properly set to null, but due to a translation error they have been assigned values of exactly 0 in TIC v5 at MAST.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up to date TIC information is available from the &lt;a href="http://archive.stsci.edu/tess/tic_doc.html"&gt;MAST TIC documentation page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>ExoFOP-TESS now online</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/exofop-tess-now-online.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-01T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-01T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Elisa Quintana</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-08-01:/docs/tess/exofop-tess-now-online.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://exofop.ipac.caltech.edu/tess/"&gt;ExoFOP-TESS&lt;/a&gt; is a web-based service developed and operated by the &lt;a href="http://nexsci.caltech.edu"&gt;NASA Exoplanet Science Institute&lt;/a&gt; (NExScI) and the &lt;a href="https://exoplanetarchive.ipac.caltech.edu"&gt;NASA Exoplanet Archive&lt;/a&gt; to optimize resources and facilitate collaboration in follow-up studies of targets observed by TESS. &lt;a href="https://exofop.ipac.caltech.edu"&gt;ExoFOP&lt;/a&gt; serves as a repository for community-gathered follow-up data by allowing upload and display of data …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://exofop.ipac.caltech.edu/tess/"&gt;ExoFOP-TESS&lt;/a&gt; is a web-based service developed and operated by the &lt;a href="http://nexsci.caltech.edu"&gt;NASA Exoplanet Science Institute&lt;/a&gt; (NExScI) and the &lt;a href="https://exoplanetarchive.ipac.caltech.edu"&gt;NASA Exoplanet Archive&lt;/a&gt; to optimize resources and facilitate collaboration in follow-up studies of targets observed by TESS. &lt;a href="https://exofop.ipac.caltech.edu"&gt;ExoFOP&lt;/a&gt; serves as a repository for community-gathered follow-up data by allowing upload and display of data and derived astrophysical parameters, and has been widely used by the Kepler and K2 Follow-Up Observation Programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the initial release of &lt;a href="https://exofop.ipac.caltech.edu/tess/"&gt;ExoFOP-TESS&lt;/a&gt;, overview pages for each of the 10.8 million stars in the &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html#candidate-target-list-ctl"&gt;TESS Candidate Target list (CTL)&lt;/a&gt; have been created. These pages contain data from the TESS Input Catalog (TIC) Version 5, including coordinates, magnitudes, stellar parameters, and planet parameters (if available). The pages also contain external links to other archives, and all content can be viewed without logging in. The ability to upload data and parameters and to search the CTL targets will be coming soon. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See our &lt;a href="followup.html#exoplanet-follow-up-observing-program-exofop"&gt;ExoFOP-TESS&lt;/a&gt; page for more details.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>TESS Guest Investigator Cycle 1 released</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-guest-investigator-cycle-1-released.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-29T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-06-29T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-06-29:/docs/tess/tess-guest-investigator-cycle-1-released.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE: the proposal deadline has been changed to October 6, 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://nspires.nasaprs.com/external/solicitations/summary.do?method=init&amp;amp;solId={7136D288-E4F8-8657-F280-6A4318467883}&amp;amp;path=open"&gt;Cycle 1 proposal call&lt;/a&gt; was released today. The &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html"&gt;TESS Guest Investigator (GI) Program&lt;/a&gt; solicits proposals for the acquisition and analysis of scientific data from the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) mission, a NASA Explorer mission currently scheduled for …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE: the proposal deadline has been changed to October 6, 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://nspires.nasaprs.com/external/solicitations/summary.do?method=init&amp;amp;solId={7136D288-E4F8-8657-F280-6A4318467883}&amp;amp;path=open"&gt;Cycle 1 proposal call&lt;/a&gt; was released today. The &lt;a href="proposing-investigations.html"&gt;TESS Guest Investigator (GI) Program&lt;/a&gt; solicits proposals for the acquisition and analysis of scientific data from the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) mission, a NASA Explorer mission currently scheduled for launch no later than June 2018. In a 2-year, near all-sky survey, TESS will monitor the brightness of nearby, bright F, G, K, and M stars in order to photometrically search for transiting planets smaller than Neptune. TESS will monitor the brightness of more than 200,000 stars spread over the celestial sphere with a photometric sensitivity sufficient to permit detection of transiting planets with radii less than 2.5 Earth radii. The mission’s high-precision, continuous baseline photometric capability is also well suited for variability and asteroseismology research and analyses of both Galactic and extragalactic astrophysical sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Observations associated with the TESS Guest Investigator (GI) Cycle 1 solicitation will begin immediately following the successful ~60-day scientific commissioning of the spacecraft. Proposals submitted to this program should be for new science investigations of the southern ecliptic hemisphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phase-1 proposals are due by 4:30 pm Eastern time on September 29, 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>TESS Science Support Center at KepSciCon</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-science-support-center-at-kepscicon.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-16T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-06-16T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-06-16:/docs/tess/tess-science-support-center-at-kepscicon.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We will be hosting a breakout session at the Kepler Science Conference, at NASA Ames, CA.
The session will be at 1.30pm on Wednesday Jun 21 and will focus on allowing the community to talk directly to the TESS Science Support Center team, and additionally talk to the folks …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We will be hosting a breakout session at the Kepler Science Conference, at NASA Ames, CA.
The session will be at 1.30pm on Wednesday Jun 21 and will focus on allowing the community to talk directly to the TESS Science Support Center team, and additionally talk to the folks from the ExoFOP team. So please come along, and engage. We might also have some coloring books and stickers.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>TESS team at AAS 230</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-team-at-aas-230.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-15T10:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-05-15T10:01:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-05-15:/docs/tess/tess-team-at-aas-230.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://aas.org/meetings/aas230"&gt;230th American Astronomical Society&lt;/a&gt; is just around the corner. Team members from TESS's Science Support Center will be there to represent the mission. Come find us at at our booth where we will be joined by NExScI, Kepler/K2 and the Exoplanet Program Office. We will be available to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://aas.org/meetings/aas230"&gt;230th American Astronomical Society&lt;/a&gt; is just around the corner. Team members from TESS's Science Support Center will be there to represent the mission. Come find us at at our booth where we will be joined by NExScI, Kepler/K2 and the Exoplanet Program Office. We will be available to answer your questions and help you understand the feasibility of planned observations.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>TESS Observatory Guide now available</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tess-observatory-guide-now-available.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-28T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-28T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Josh Schlieder</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-04-28:/docs/tess/tess-observatory-guide-now-available.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;To aid in the development in potential TESS science investigations we have created a &lt;a href="docs/TESS_observatory_guide_v1.1.pdf"&gt;TESS Observatory Guide&lt;/a&gt;. This document serves two purposes. The first is to provide a comprehensive description of the TESS  observatory design, operations, and capabilities. The second is to provide potential proposers detailed information relevant to preparing …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;To aid in the development in potential TESS science investigations we have created a &lt;a href="docs/TESS_observatory_guide_v1.1.pdf"&gt;TESS Observatory Guide&lt;/a&gt;. This document serves two purposes. The first is to provide a comprehensive description of the TESS  observatory design, operations, and capabilities. The second is to provide potential proposers detailed information relevant to preparing proposals for the  TESS GI program. This includes descriptions of  TESS data processing and data products and GI program procedures, services, and tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a living document. Comments are greatly appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Volunteer to review proposals</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/volunteer-to-review-proposals.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-28T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-28T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-04-28:/docs/tess/volunteer-to-review-proposals.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Science Support Center is responsible for organizing the review of proposals submitted to the TESS Guest Investigator program. Our first cycle deadline will be on September 29, 2017, with the in-person peer review likely taking place in mid-December. We are currently looking for volunteers with expertise in astrophysics …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Science Support Center is responsible for organizing the review of proposals submitted to the TESS Guest Investigator program. Our first cycle deadline will be on September 29, 2017, with the in-person peer review likely taking place in mid-December. We are currently looking for volunteers with expertise in astrophysics and exoplanet science to serve on our review panel. The requirements are that you have a PhD or relevant experience (so this opportunity isn't open to graduate students), and that you are not intending to PI a TESS Cycle 1 proposal (it's fine if you later choose to submit a proposal, but we would then not invite you to the review). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please get in touch by sending your name, institution, and areas of expertise to &lt;a href="mailto:tessgi@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov"&gt;tessgi@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov&lt;/a&gt;, or filling in &lt;a href="https://goo.gl/forms/p4ZqiTQSEHjbM6nz2"&gt;this form&lt;/a&gt;. As a guide, we are anticipating having panels made up of an approximately 50/50 split between postdocs and more senior scientists. Topics we are particularly interested in recruiting reviewers for are exoplanet science, asteroseismology, stellar activity, binary stars, and supernova observations. &lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Tell us about the software tool and data products you would like</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/tell-us-about-the-software-tool-and-data-products-you-would-like.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-21T14:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-21T14:01:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-04-21:/docs/tess/tell-us-about-the-software-tool-and-data-products-you-would-like.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Science Support Center at NASA Goddard is currently collecting input from the scientific community on what tools and data products you would like to see developed. We have some plans but we are seeking more input. What do you need to achieve your science goals? Get in touch …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS Science Support Center at NASA Goddard is currently collecting input from the scientific community on what tools and data products you would like to see developed. We have some plans but we are seeking more input. What do you need to achieve your science goals? Get in touch at &lt;a href="mailto:tessgi@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov"&gt;tessgi@bigbang.gsfc.nasa.gov&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Space hardware development and going well</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/space-hardware-development-and-going-well.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-17T10:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-17T10:01:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-04-17:/docs/tess/space-hardware-development-and-going-well.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS hardware development is progressing well. All four cameras are currently being tested and are performing as expected. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TESS is a NASA Explorer class mission.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The TESS hardware development is progressing well. All four cameras are currently being tested and are performing as expected. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TESS is a NASA Explorer class mission.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Development of new TESS website</title><link href="https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/development-of-new-tess-website.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-17T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-17T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tom Barclay</name></author><id>tag:heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov,2017-04-17:/docs/tess/development-of-new-tess-website.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) Science Support Center team is transitioning to a new website. This is that website. Lots of content on the Guest Investigator program is coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) Science Support Center team is transitioning to a new website. This is that website. Lots of content on the Guest Investigator program is coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>